<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dataroot xmlns:od="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:officedata" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="events.xsd" generated="2009-11-11T14:01:22">
<events>
<key>3_colour_printing</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Three-colour Printing</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Jakob Le Blon, a German artist and engraver of French extraction, has produced a colour mezzotint using three different colours combined. Le Blon produced a separate plate of yellow, red and blue - estimating the amount of each colour required in each part of the engraving entirely by eye. The result is a truly amazing innovation, making him a pioneer in the field of printing and colour separation.</event_text>
<historical_date>1702</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBQAAAJDTqvEIAAAAkNOq8QQAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEGAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{3459FEDC-5B10-4DA5-A071-6E334D199218}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QkAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>air_loom</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Air Loom Gang</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Tea merchant and self-styled political emissary James Tilly Matthews, recently released by the French (after their efforts to ignore him failed and imprisonment seemed the only way to keep him quiet), has warned of a sinister plot to undermine the government in London. A shadowy band of &quot;magnetic spies&quot; - the &quot;Air Loom Gang&quot; - are said to have perfected the &quot;Air Loom&quot;: a diabolical mesmerism machine able to influence and persecute individuals from a distance through the medium of animal magnetism.\n\nThe malign effects of the Air Loom, what Tilly refers to as &quot;torture-at-a-distance&quot;, are evidenced by &quot;foot-curving, lethargy-making, spark-exploding, knee-nailing, burning out, eye-screwing&quot;. The unfortunate Matthews now proclaims himself a victim of these symptoms, doubtless as a result of attempts by the pitiless gang to silence his momentous revelations.\n\nUndeterred, the gallant Mr Matthews recently took the matter to the House of Commons, crying &quot;Treason!&quot; at the Home Office minister, whom he felt to be implicated in the plot. Shortly afterwards he was removed from the House, and is currently residing in the nearby Bethlem Hospital for those not entirely connected to the real world.</event_text>
<historical_date>1793</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDQAAADQJx44SAAAAkNOq8QMAAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{2762F0CB-5814-46CB-8004-76A57B871543}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhIAAACQ06rxEQAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>alcoholic_apothecary</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>An Unusual Bedside Manner</onscreen_name>
<event_text>George Fordyce is a doctor whose liking for a drink has bestowed upon him an unusual bedside manner.\n\nOnce called to the bedside of a lady whilst under the influence, he was actually too inebriated to take her pulse properly, and muttered &quot;Drunk by Jove!&quot; to himself - before leaving in a hurry. The following day, Fordyce, expecting to be reprimanded for his conduct, arrived completely sober and entered the lady’s room with trepidation. Imagine his surprise when his charge confirmed his diagnosis, begged his forgiveness, and gave him one hundred pounds and a promise to abstain from the bottle from then on!</event_text>
<historical_date>1794</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QQAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D901786B-293C-448F-A57B-E8A3A46A230C}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>alcoholic_apothecary_dies</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>An Unusual Dietary Arrangement</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Dr George Fordyce has led an unusual life. Having studied the eating patterns of lions, he became convinced that man need not eat more than a single meal each day, provided that meal was of sufficient quantity and contained plenty of meat.\n\nEvery day at four o&apos;clock for the last twenty years, Fordyce has been to Dolly’s Chop House in Paternoster Row and ordered: a one and a half pound rump steak, half a chicken, a plate of boned fish, a pint of ale, quarter of a pint of brandy, and a bottle of port.\n\nBefore setting out on his medical rounds, Fordyce would then go on to three separate coffee houses, consuming a large glass of brandy at each. Unfortunately Dr Fordyce has just died of gout, unconnected to his diet of course.</event_text>
<historical_date>1800</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxBQAAAJDTqvEIAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QQAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEGAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{1C6750BF-D907-41DD-9B74-304659A00482}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QoAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>american_blizzard</key>
<picture_category>disaster_eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>New England Blizzard</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A furious storm has hit New England, continuing for over a week and stopping for no more than an hour or two.\n\nHeavy snow in nearby forests has driven wild animals toward settlements - in turn threatening livestock and food supply. Pastured cattle have frozen to death in snow drifts that have covered houses to their third storeys, and made barns accessible only through their hay lofts. People have even resorted to burning their furniture as they are unable to reach their wood supplies, and food has been scarce for those who rely on the local farmer to deliver it to them.</event_text>
<historical_date>1717</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>disaster_eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBgAAAJDTqvEJAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QUAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEHAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{9E690AFA-FD03-4277-8178-06D4CF60B563}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QoAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>amish_to_america</key>
<picture_category>fleet1.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Amish to America</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Following extensive persecution in their native lands for their practices of adult baptism and opposition to the union of church and state, the Amish have been granted safe haven in America by prominent Quaker William Penn.\n\nA radical sect of Mennonites from Switzerland and the Palatinate, the Amish are regularly martyred there by an intolerant opposition - oft by tying them in sacks and throwing them into rivers to drown. As their very existence is under threat, the Amish are moving to Pennsylvania en masse at the invite of William Penn - as part of his &quot;holy experiment&quot; in religious tolerance.</event_text>
<historical_date>1727</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>fleet1.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceODAAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAADQJx44NAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{3CF3944F-A67B-4247-AD95-E71446AF2594}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjg0AAACQ06rxCwAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>ascending_mont_blanc</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Ascent of Mont Blanc</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Savoyard mountaineers Dr Michel Paccard and his guide Jacques Balmat have completed a successful ascent of Mont Blanc, highest of the Alps and the most treacherous climb amongst them.\n\nCompleting a challenge first set out a quarter of a century before by the scientist Horace-Benedict Saussure, Paccard planned the expedition in detail for three years. Intending to gather accurate information about the true height of the peak, he studied the grand plateau of the mountain with binoculars in order to gather information on weather patterns, and the likelihood of avalanches occurring.\n\nAfter recruiting Balmat and following a hazardous climb of almost three days, they finally reached the summit. Once there, Paccard was unable to gather the information he wanted due to damage to his barometer. Unable to find shelter and snowblind, he was led back down to their bivouac by Balmat, returning safely to the valley the following afternoon.</event_text>
<historical_date>1786</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{76B5BA52-0C33-4973-8821-1C71A80DC5D5}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>ascending_triglav</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Ascent of Mount Triglav</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The entrepreneur and natural scientist Baron Sigmund Zois has funded many scientific and cultural works in the name of enlightenment. His sponsorship of the expedition to scale Mount Triglav, the highest peak in Slovenia, is no different. Four local climbers have successfully completed the climb, a source of pride across the entire Empire.</event_text>
<historical_date>1778</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{52820B67-70A6-4263-A2BB-EA0A4BF92558}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>astronomical_aberration</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Astronomical Aberration</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The aberration of light - giving the stars and planets the impression of movement - has been discovered by Astronomer Royal James Bradley.\n\nBradley postulates that at the moment of observation, the position of any celestial body is displaced according to the finite speed of light and the velocity of the body upon which the observer stands - in this case the Earth, which can of course vary according to its orbit around the Sun.</event_text>
<historical_date>1729</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;royal_observatory&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvECAAAAkNOq8QYAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{DED5E3F3-06E5-444E-BB3E-7DDB7E19BD99}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>australia_day</key>
<picture_category>fleet1.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Transportation to Australia</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The first fleet of convicts has arrived to form the new British penal colony in Botany Bay, New South Wales.\n\nEleven ships carrying around fifteen hundred people have finally arrived after a punishing journey of eleven months. Governor Arthur Phillip arrived ahead of the fleet and found that the bay did not live up to his expectations, there being little fresh water and poor soil.\n\nScouting further north along the coast they have found a more suitable site for habitation, naming it Port Jackson. The convicts have been set to work building their own dwellings and preparing the soil for agriculture.</event_text>
<historical_date>1788</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>fleet1.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceODQAAAJDTqvEJAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAADQJx44NAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{CE116C5D-E79D-4BBD-B281-6E780C16C380}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjg0AAACQ06rxCgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>autobiography_colley_cibber</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Apology for the Life of Colley Cibber</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The actor, theatre manager, and some-time poet Colley Cibber has become an unwitting literary trailblazer through the publication of his &quot;autobiography&quot; - a seemingly random collection of anecdotes and memoirs about his extraordinary life.\n\nAlthough the piece is rife with unreliable chronology, scant regard for the facts, and a degree of total fabrication, it remains useful as a unique record of the personalities and goings-on in the London theatres of the late seventeenth century.\n\nCibber, the son of an expatriate Danish sculptor, entered the theatre as a reaction against his parents&apos; desire that he enter the clergy, and has developed a reputation for excellence in comedic roles, but is much-maligned as a tragic actor.</event_text>
<historical_date>1740</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{39883EC8-995C-4D43-96C5-4863F43FE91D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bach_brandenburg_concertos</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Brandenburg Concertos</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The noted composer Johann Sebastian Bach has presented six instrumental works to the Margrave of Brandenburg-Schwedt, originally under the title of &quot;six concertos with many instruments&quot; - soon to be more commonly known as the &quot;Brandenburg Concertos&quot;.\n\nCritics have noted that the pieces contain the &quot;widest spectrum of orchestral instruments in daring combinations&quot;, and that &quot;every one of the six concertos sets a precedent in scoring&quot;. No doubt Bach hopes to gain patronage from the Margrave, a long-standing patron of music and the arts.</event_text>
<historical_date>1721</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QMAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{9B981643-4AD9-41EB-A086-9DF6F2763F35}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bach_dies</key>
<picture_category>small funeral-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Bach Dies</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Johannes Sebastian Bach, the great composer, has died at the age of sixty-five.\n\nHis health had been in general decline for some time, to the extent where his employer - the Elector of Saxony - had already been searching for a replacement Kapellmeister from the burgomaster at Leipzig. Bach’s eyesight in particular had become very poor, and so the British Opthalmologist John Taylor attempted an operation to correct it - sadly during which the composer died.\n\nMany in the press seem content to blame the surgeon for Bach’s death, whereas other more reasonable reports have suggested Bach was killed by a stroke brought on by the pneumonia he was known to suffer from. He leaves a body of work containing more than one thousand pieces.</event_text>
<historical_date>1750</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>small funeral-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceODwAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAADQJx44QAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{4F8FFE7D-1B82-4690-A78A-30FD78CED448}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhAAAACQ06rxDgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bach_toccata_and_fugue_in_d_minor</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Toccata and Fugue in D Minor</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Staying in the town of Arnstadt, Thuringia, noted organ player Johann Sebastian Bach has produced something of a minor classic in his &quot;Toccata and Fugue in D Minor&quot;.\n\nRecently, Bach has been in thrall to the organ master Dieterich Buxtehude, eventually walking the two hundred and fifty miles to Lubeck in order to visit him at his home! Buxtehude has been an enormous influence on Bach’s style of composition, and the young composer stayed several months longer than intended in order to pick up as much as possible from the old master.</event_text>
<historical_date>1707</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{86F7DE0A-BEE0-4363-8AA3-136158F43FD3}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bach_well_tempered_clavier_1</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>First Volume of Bach&apos;s Well-tempered Clavier</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Now living in Kothen under the patronage of Prince Leopold von Anhalt-Köthen, his Kapellmeister Johannes Sebastian Bach has produced a collection of pieces entitled &quot;The Well-Tempered Clavier&quot; - intended &quot;for the profit and use of musical youth desirous of learning, and especially for the pastime of those already skilled in this study&quot;.\n\nContaining twenty-four pairs of preludes and fugues, the first pair are in the key of C Major, the second in C Minor, the third in C# Major, and so on in a chromatic pattern across the entire scale. No doubt this collection will prove to be a useful tool for the development of any music student, as the pieces can easily be transposed for stringed instruments.</event_text>
<historical_date>1722</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvERAAAAkNOq8RAAAAA0CceOEwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{448E2E97-8393-4C11-BD2B-91D5DEAEBF66}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhMAAACQ06rxEgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bach_well_tempered_clavier_2</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Second Volume of Bach&apos;s Well-tempered Clavier</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The great composer Johannes Sebastian Bach has produced a second volume of his &quot;Twenty-Four Preludes and Fugues&quot;.\n\nTo the educated observer, the work appears to be a natural companion piece to his earlier &quot;The Well-Tempered Clavier&quot;, and has already been referred to as &quot;Book Two&quot;, although the composer has not indicated as such.</event_text>
<historical_date>1744</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{0876D6BB-5056-43A6-BDDB-7ADD293AED9E}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>ballistics_advanced</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>New Principles in Gunnery</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Quaker engineer and mathematician Benjamin Robins has completed his experiments with ballistics and fortification, publishing the results as &quot;New Principles in Gunnery&quot;. Included in this volume are his notes on the motion of projectiles and the air’s resistance to them, the ranges of mortars and cannon, the flight of rockets, and the advantages of &quot;rifled&quot; gun barrels.</event_text>
<historical_date>1742</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>[FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;france&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;austria&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;spain&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;prussia&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;russia&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;ottomans&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;netherlands&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;maratha&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;mughal&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;sweden&quot;, &quot;gunnery_school&quot;)]</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBQAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAAA0CceOEgAAAJDTqvEGAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{65FDD761-7B57-4CF9-9860-AB4879EA7B44}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhIAAACQ06rxEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bangorian_controversy</key>
<picture_category>Religion_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Bangorian Controversy</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Benjamin Hoadly, the Bishop of Bangor, has caused a theological argument during delivery of a sermon to the monarch, quoting from John 18:36 - &quot;My kingdom is not of this world&quot;.\n\nHoadly has reinforced the current royal view regarding the separation of church and state - that the Lord has not delegated authority to individuals, and the church should be concerned only with the kingdom of heaven - leaving government to the ruler and their parliament.\n\nImmediate counter-attacks have been made, and the Convocation has created a committee to investigate the matter further.</event_text>
<historical_date>1717</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionTechExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;enlightenment_secular_humanism&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>Religion_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBAAAAJDTqvEIAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEFAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{24DA9E02-5516-4E9B-85C4-A199CBCAE3F8}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QoAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bavarian_illuminai</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Bavarian Illuminati</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Founded in 1776 by lawyer Adam Weishaupt in Ingolstadt, Bavaria; the so-called &quot;Illuminati&quot; has been forced underground by decree of the Elector Palatine, who has banned all such &quot;secret&quot; societies from practicing freely in his lands.\n\nIt has long been the suspicion of his ministers that such societies are seeking to undermine and bring down the accepted order of government within society, something that will simply not do! The Elector is an enlightened man, and right-thinking men surely trust his ability to steer the ship of state through waters both troubled and calm.\n\nWhether the society’s two thousand reputed members across the continent will disband or continue to practice in secret we may never know, as with the effects of their allegedly nefarious attempts to influence world affairs.</event_text>
<historical_date>1784</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEEAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{301BE964-0D67-41E5-AC1D-2327624B30DC}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>belfast_news_letter_published</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Belfast News Letter</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The Belfast News Letter has been published for the first time under the sign of the peacock in Bridge Street. Known simply as &quot;The News Letter&quot;, the paper will be distributed all over Ireland and will take the position of an advocate of union with England, as opposed to the more seditious, nationalistic view of rival publications.</event_text>
<historical_date>1737</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>1</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBgAAAJDTqvEJAAAAkNOq8QUAAACQ06rxAQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEHAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{E407AE50-15A6-454F-B121-C8BA41B0E08D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QkAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bellamy_killed</key>
<picture_category>pirates afterloose.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>&quot;Black Sam&quot; Bellamy</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Twenty eight year old pirate captain &quot;Black Sam&quot; Bellamy - so called as he did not wear a white powdered wig, instead growing his own black hair - has been shipwrecked on a sandbar off the coast of New England with his flagship Whydah and prize ships laden with booty. Just nine men have survived the wrecks, seven of whom have already been picked up and will stand trial for piracy.\n\nBellamy began his career trying to salvage some of the many shipwrecks along the Florida coastline, but soon turned to piracy when his chosen line of work proved fruitless. Joining the crew of Benjamin Hornigold, Bellamy soon proved his mettle and usurped power and command of the ship Marianne. Before long a second ship, Sultana, was taken - exchanged for the three-hundred ton slaver Whydah shortly after that.\n\nThroughout his short career in piracy, Bellamy became known for his kindness, mercy and generosity - both to his victims and the men who served with him - earning him the name the &quot;Prince of Pirates&quot;.</event_text>
<historical_date>1717</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>pirates afterloose.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAAA0CceOEAAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDAAAADQJx44PAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D6BA4591-41E0-4253-B308-6BC008F253E1}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhAAAACQ06rxDgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>biathlon_norway</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Winter Sport Biathlon</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Originally intended as a method of training for soldiers in Norway, the first winter biathlon for sport has taken place. Combining cross-country skiing and target shooting, the first competitors are different border patrol regiments. Due to the success of the event plans are afoot to extend the competition to a summer variant also.</event_text>
<historical_date>1767</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>1</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBgAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxAQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QUAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEHAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{54A006A1-EF0E-46CC-B432-67C378C1EC6C}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QoAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>big_bottom_massacre</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Big Bottom Incident</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Big Bottom, a new settlement on the Muskingum River in Ohio, has come under attack from a native war party, resulting in the brutal deaths of eleven men, one woman and two children; as well as the capture of three others. A handful of survivors were forced to flee for their lives.\n\nDespite the existence of a treaty between native tribes and settlers, areas in Ohio are still disputed. This has not stopped the Ohio Company of Associates from proceeding with its program of settlement there however, although the financial strain has led to under-investment. This regrettable situation may go some way towards explaining why the settlers kept such a poor watch over Big Bottom, and why they had not even completed the construction of the blockhouse.\n\nThe tragedy could have been much worse if not for the actions of Colonel William Stacy of Marietta, who skated thirty miles up the icy river to bring word of the impending attack to his two sons, only one of whom was to survive the massacre.</event_text>
<historical_date>1791</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxBgAAAJDTqvEJAAAAkNOq8QMAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEHAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D28D67A1-FECA-4287-AA09-E2E6E7F7D90D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QoAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bioelectricity_discovered</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Bioelectricity Discovered</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The anatomist Luigi Galvani has become the first man to investigate the presence of electricity in the muscles of animals.\n\nWhilst cutting a frog’s leg his assistant’s scalpel accidentally touched the copper hook the animal was hanging from. This resulted in a twitching of the muscles in the frog’s leg. Galvani was fascinated, soon discovering that simply touching the end of the scalpel to the nerve - with the other end touching the power source - was enough to cause the same involuntary movement in the dead frog. From this he has concluded that there is a relationship between the &quot;animal electricity&quot; flowing through animal bodies and the movement of their muscles.</event_text>
<historical_date>1768</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEDAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{80C22689-2DC7-45A4-B4B6-D0A081BEBFCF}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>blackbeard_killed</key>
<picture_category>pirates afterloose.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Blackbeard Finally Killed</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The vicious pirate Edward Teach - known to all as Blackbeard - has finally been defeated and killed in battle with the Royal Navy. Even though he had been pardoned under the recent Act of Grace, Blackbeard was still targeted as a dangerous freebooter by the Governor of Virginia - who commissioned two sloops under the command of Lieutenant Maynard to track him down.\n\nEventually finding Blackbeard’s ship in a North Carolina inlet, Maynard attacked Teach’s ship Adventure, giving chase as it attempted to cut anchor and escape. Managing to fire on Adventure’s rigging and forcing it ashore, Maynard ordered his crew below so that Blackbeard would board his sloop. As predicted, he took the bait and boarded with ten men, unprepared for the attack of Maynard’s men.\n\nDuring the fighting, Blackbeard was cornered and eventually killed by blood loss from multiple sword blows and gunshot wounds. His head was later hacked off and hung from the bow of the sloop.</event_text>
<historical_date>1718</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>pirates afterloose.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QQAAAA0CceOEQAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDgAAADQJx44RAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{50B9ABB8-2D04-49B7-A43E-9017783442BB}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhEAAACQ06rxEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>blood_pressure</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Blood Pressure Taken</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The Reverend Stephen Hales of Teddington has long been respected for his detailed scientific studies of the natural world. Building on his previous work concerning the pressure of sap in plants and the transpiration of moisture from the leaves, he has now discerned a natural pressure in the blood of living creatures.\n\nHis method of testing is to insert a brass pipe into the artery of a horse, to which a glass tube is attached, then observing that the blood within the tube could be seen to rise - and has concluded that this must be due to pressure.\n\nPresently, the method of observing this phenomenon is highly invasive, so the medical benefits of this discovery may take a while to present themselves.</event_text>
<historical_date>1726</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionTechExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;industry_agriculture_improved_animal_husbandry&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{1BDC5FE7-9F09-4FDB-81DA-007AF745E43D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bonnet_hanged</key>
<picture_category>pirates afterloose.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Gentleman Pirate</onscreen_name>
<event_text>So named due to his background of moderate wealth through landownership, the &quot;Gentleman Pirate&quot; - Stede Bonnet, an associate of Blackbeard amongst others - has been captured and executed for buccaneering in the Caribbean.\n\nAlready pardoned by the Governor of North Carolina, and issued a letter of marque to privateer against the Spanish, Bonnet soon returned to piracy in 1718. The Governor of South Carolina tasked Colonel William Rhett with bringing Bonnet and his crew to justice. Rhett came upon Bonnet’s ship whilst it was being repaired on the Cape Fear River. A furious battle ensued that lasted several hours before the massively outnumbered pirates surrendered.\n\nAfter being held for three weeks, Bonnet was sentenced to death on two counts of piracy following the betrayal of a crew member who turned King&apos;s Evidence against him in return for the sparing of his own life. As a last resort, Bonnet wrote to the Governor of South Carolina to ask for clemency - a move which proved fruitless as the Governor endorsed the Judge’s decision, and Bonnet was hanged without delay.</event_text>
<historical_date>1718</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>pirates afterloose.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAAA0CceOEAAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDQAAADQJx44QAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{A0775F18-B31C-499B-9BC0-C06826204477}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhAAAACQ06rxDwAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>bow_street_runners</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Bow Street Runners</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Eight men have been recruited to act as a bolster to the will of the Bow Street courts at the behest of dramatist and magistrate Henry Fielding - and paid for directly from government funds.\n\nIt is this official link to the courts that differentiates them from the now-common thief-takers, and also goes some way to curtailing the widespread corruption that remains rife in that profession. The Bow Street Runners do not patrol the streets, instead arresting perpetrators on the direct authority of magistrates and travelling the length and breadth of the country in order to pursue specific individuals wanted for prosecution.\n\nThis law enforcement innovation is the first step towards greater control over the spiralling crime rates in the capital and other major urban centres.</event_text>
<historical_date>1748</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;governors_residence&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBQAAAJDTqvEJAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEGAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{8A62A376-38B2-48B5-A996-7590478CDB3B}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QoAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>british_museum</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The British Museum</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The natural historian and occasional doctor of medicine Sir Hans Sloane has bequeathed his large collection of curious objects to the nation, including many books, manuscripts, drawings and pressings. They are to be housed in a special museum for everyone to see, including a reading room for scholars. It has also been decreed that the museum will receive a copy of every book printed from now on.\n\nAfter much deliberation and the rejection of Buckingham House, the trustees have decided on Montagu House as a suitable venue, purchasing the house for twenty thousand pounds.</event_text>
<historical_date>1753</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;great_museum&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{B2717A2A-A219-4905-B169-7791B80C90B5}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>brotherhood_of_the_wolf</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Beast of Gevaudan</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Described as a wolf-like creature as large as a cow, with a tuft of hair almost like a lion’s mane, a long tail and a black stripe down its back; the infamous beast of Gevaudan has finally been put down! Following over two years of brutally maiming and killing the local population, and a failed attempt to kill it by professional wolf hunters, local man Jean Chastel has been credited with bringing down the beast. Supposedly it appeared before him whilst he was reading the bible, and apparently Chastel finished his prayer before slaying the creature.\n\nWhether this is true remains to be seen as the animal’s body has not been recovered. However the killings have stopped, for the time-being at least.</event_text>
<historical_date>1767</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{157639E3-DCD8-4F6C-9102-5B7D5192269C}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>broughton_rules</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The London Prize Ring Rules</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Jack Broughton, first prizefighting champion of England at the heavyweight level, has defined a set of seven rules governing bare-knuckle boxing encounters at his London amphitheatre.\n\nThough Broughton holds no official station beyond the stature due to his title, these rules have quickly found favour with proponents of the pugilistic art. Prior to this, many such encounters were little more than chaotic free-for-alls, frequently with fatal consequences. This is not to say that Broughton’s rules wholly dispense with the raw nature of proceedings - throws and falls are still permissible, rounds last for as long as both fighters remain on their feet, the number of rounds is limited only by the protagonists ability to come up to scratch in time, and no allowance is made for injuries - however serious.\n\nBroughton’s rules are known as the &quot;London Prize Ring&quot; rules, and have set the fledgling sport on a path toward acceptability.</event_text>
<historical_date>1743</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxBgAAAJDTqvEJAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEHAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6F35FFB7-C15B-49D2-8504-678B5DAFB4D7}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QoAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>calendar_changes</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>New Year&apos;s Day</onscreen_name>
<event_text>For over five centuries 25th March - or Lady Day - has marked the beginning of the new year. Lady Day is a celebration of the Annunciation - when it was revealed by the Angel Gabriel that Mary would conceive the Christ child.\n\nUpon its recent adoption of the Gregorian Calendar, Britain has controversially followed Catholic Europe&apos;s example and changed New Year&apos;s Day to January 1st - so now Easter will be celebrated around the anniversary of the First Council of Nicaea - and meaning that the British year now matches that of it&apos;s continental neighbours. Rumour has it that this change is also partly motivated by embarrassment, as having a calendar out of step with almost everyone else was causing problems for both traders and generals alike!\n\nThe upshot of this change is that the average man is suddenly concerned with the whereabouts of the &quot;missing&quot; eleven days he feels have been taken away from him, and the injustice of having his life unreasonably and inexplicably &quot;shortened&quot; against his will!</event_text>
<historical_date>1751</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{E91A0AB0-4547-460D-BED3-C7C44D1314D3}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>cast_steel</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>New Casting Technique</onscreen_name>
<event_text>While searching for a better kind of steel to use in his workings, clockmaker Benjamin Huntsman has discovered a process for producing harder, purer steel than any currently in production.\n\nWhile the details are a closely guarded secret, it is known that the method involves heating and cooling iron in large clay crucibles. To obtain a cheaper source for the coke that fuels his furnaces, Mr. Huntsman has recently relocated to Handsworth, near Sheffield. Certainly the cutlery makers of that town will benefit from the close proximity of this high quality &quot;crucible steel&quot;.\n\nHowever, it should be noted that whereas this is an innovation in the West, steel of this quality - or &quot;wootz&quot; - has been produced in India for generations. Indeed, the Indian process uses crucibles in a remarkably similar way and has apparently been practiced since the fourth century.</event_text>
<historical_date>1735</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;ironmasters_works&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEGAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{1DA9F039-F5B8-490B-B521-962194B0D205}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>celsius_scale</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>New Temperature Scale</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences has received a paper from Anders Celsius, Professor of Astronomy at Uppsala University, entitled &quot;Observations of two persistent degrees on a thermometer&quot;.\n\nCelsius, already celebrated as the founder of the Uppsala Astronomical Observatory and for his detailed studies of the Aurora Borealis, proposes a scale of temperature measurement in which the boiling point of water is denoted as zero and its freezing point as one hundred.\n\nIn addition, Celsius has also determined that the boiling point of water changes according to atmospheric pressure, and that its freezing point is independent of outside factors.</event_text>
<historical_date>1741</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{71614002-811A-474C-890B-5496BECD73C3}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>cheese_revolution</key>
<picture_category>shipyard.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>A Change of Cheese</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The navy has always held supplies of Suffolk Cheese or &quot;Suffolk Bang&quot;, a durable &quot;flet&quot; cheese - made from milk already skimmed for butter production. Unfortunately, being virtually inedible, it is said that &quot;hunger can break through everything except Suffolk Cheese&quot;.\n\nAfter frequent complaints about it the navy has decided to move over to supplying ships with Cheshire and Gloucester Cheese instead, full-fat cheeses of greater flavour - although much more expensive and with a shorter shelf-life.</event_text>
<historical_date>1758</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;military_navy_preserved_foods&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>shipyard.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAAA0CceOEQAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDwAAADQJx44SAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{94A59447-E659-42B6-9214-EDA9EFC364CB}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhIAAACQ06rxEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>chlorine_disinfectant</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>A Chemical Discovery</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Chemistry as a science is gradually becoming as important as physics and astronomy. Swedish apothecary Carl Wilhelm Scheele has discovered a green gas, poisonous with a strong odour and the ability to bleach the colour from flowers that are immersed in it.\n\nThe gas is obtained by treating a sample of manganese ore with hydrochloric acid, and has been named &quot;dephlogisticated muriatic acid&quot; - a name that is sure to catch on.</event_text>
<historical_date>1773</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{474F5B10-DA8E-43E2-A5C4-2F4868DAEBF4}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>circular_saw</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Table-mounted Saw</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A patent for a &quot;saw windmill&quot; has been granted to Samuel Miller of Southampton. The common carpenter’s saw blade is transformed into a metal disc, with saw teeth cut into the circumference.\n\nOnce mounted on a table designed for the purpose, the disc is driven by a water wheel. Thus, it is able to rapidly incise through timbers of great strength and girth. Naval blockmaker Walter Taylor (also of Southampton) also claims he is the originator of this invention, and though he holds several patents for blockmaking, we do not know for sure who is right and who is merely a &quot;saw&quot; loser.</event_text>
<historical_date>1777</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionTechExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;industry_metal_machine_tools&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{4453E9F5-67F3-4501-8FC6-B12657B752F2}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>circus_london</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Come One, Come All!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Mr Philip Astley has opened his &quot;Amphitheatre of Equestrian Arts&quot; to an enthusiastic reception from the London crowds! By morning this facility acts as a riding school, but each afternoon an audience is thrilled and delighted by feats of extraordinary horsemanship.\n\nThe centre-piece of this attraction is a large ring, which affords uninterrupted views of the trick riders as they complete their circuits at the gallop. Late of the Fifteenth Light Dragoon Regiment, Mr Astley is an astute entrepreneur.\n\nRumours abound that he will soon be adding other attractions to the repertoire such as clowns, acrobats, musicians and jugglers; and perhaps seeking to establish his &quot;circuses&quot; in other prominent capitals.</event_text>
<historical_date>1768</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QcAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6B7B4159-38B0-4A11-A3B8-417045FF180C}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>clever_stick</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Seven Bridges of Konigsberg</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The city of Konigsberg is bisected by the river Pregel, in the midst of which are two islands. Seven bridges connect the islands to one another and with each bank of the river.\n\nMany visitors have whiled away the long cold Prussian evenings by contemplating the possibility of a walking tour of the city, starting and ending in the same location and crossing each bridge only once. Celebrated mathematician, physicist and all round spoil-sport Leonhard Euler has typically spoiled everyone&apos;s fun by solving the problem.\n\nDisappointingly, it seems that it is not possible to complete the circuit - but it is the method by which Herr Euler has proved this that has proved exciting to the numerate community. The reduction of the problem to a set of nodes and connecting arcs is seen as the genesis of &quot;graph theory&quot;.</event_text>
<historical_date>1736</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{A0543044-300E-483C-9630-25F50FCD8822}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>company_of_quenching_fire</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Company of Quenching Fire</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A devastating fire in Edinburgh has led to the introduction of a number of radical new measures in order to reduce the expenditure of insurance companies. As such they have been instrumental in the formation of the &quot;Company of Quenching Fire&quot;, a force of men specifically tasked to both prevent and fight fires within the city.\n\nIn an act of Parliament entitled &quot;Quenching of Fires and Rules to be Observed by the Inhabitants Thereanent&quot;, provision has been made for the municipal appointment of twelve firemasters. In turn each of these men has been tasked with the recruitment of a number of men to work on an auxiliary basis. However, with little money being made available for equipment or training, it would seem that the personal bravery of these recruits - and a certain amount of luck - will play a vital role until a body of experience can be built up.\n\nWhatever their limitations, the Company is the first example of an organised municipal firefighting force within Britain, and it is hoped that the idea will soon be taken up far and wide!</event_text>
<historical_date>1703</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{AAF214AF-5558-4C35-BCDC-281C858BF4C0}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>copyright_act</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Copyright Act</onscreen_name>
<event_text>&quot;An Act for the Encouragement of Learning by vesting the Copies of Printed Books in the Authors or purchasers of such Copies, during the Times therein mentioned&quot; passes into law. This is the first specific act giving vestige of the rights to reproduction of a work to its author.\n\nThis new enactment breaks the monopoly of the charter of the Stationer’s Company, which protected the rights of the printer only. The Copyright Act 1709 is the first legislation of its kind recorded in the western world.</event_text>
<historical_date>1709</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QYAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{4D8ADD3B-4138-48B5-9188-A4F6702BE072}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>cornish_cumudgeonly_ways</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Last Native Cornish Speaker Dies</onscreen_name>
<event_text>English lawyer Daines Barrington has published an account of his interview with the late Dolly Pentreath, Fishwife of Mousehole, and allegedly the last native speaker of the Cornish language.\n\nDying at the grand old age of one hundred and two, Dolly sold fish at the market place in Mousehole for many years, smoked a pipe, drank ale like a man, and had a voice so loud you could apparently hear it &quot;as far away as Newlyn&quot;. Those who crossed her recalled her swearing abuse in a long stream of Cornish, sometimes followed by an attack with her hatchet.\n\nAccording to legend, her last words were &quot;Me ne vidn cewsel Sawznek!&quot; - &quot;I do not want to speak English!&quot;</event_text>
<historical_date>1777</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{F523FD73-7415-4899-ABAE-11DBBB2E4E83}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>critique_of_pure_reason</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Critique of Pure Reason</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Immanuel Kant of Konigsberg, Prussia, has emerged from a decade of self-imposed isolation to publish his &quot;Critique of Pure Reason&quot;, a monumental work of philosophy.\n\nWhereas Herr Kant’s early career encompassed impressive astronomical discoveries, he is now more celebrated as one of the leading philosophers of the age.\n\nThe Critique is an attempt to bridge the gap between rationalism and empiricism, considering the relationship between knowledge gained by reason and that gained by experience. This theory is described by the author as &quot;transcendental idealism&quot; - in essence that empirical knowledge is real, but cannot comprehend that which transcends the cognitive faculties.</event_text>
<historical_date>1781</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{88AF3CBC-918B-46CE-A954-451E994C8BDF}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>cuckoo_clock</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Cuckoo Clock</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Although clocks featuring a mechanical cuckoo and small musical pipes to produce its distinctive call have been known for over a century, development and production of these devices has now become a significant industry in the Black Forest Mountains.\n\nNaturally, locals claim the invention for themselves, describing how a clockmaster named Franz Anton Ketterer from Schönwald was inspired by the bellows of a church organ, incorporating a miniature version puffing air into the pipes to mark each hour.\n\nWhether they are right or not the craftsmen of the Black Forest have contributed much to the artistry of these popular time-pieces - adorning clock faces with painted scenes, and carving the weights that power the mechanism into the shapes of pine cones.</event_text>
<historical_date>1738</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{F3B8FCB7-D85E-4599-BD26-4EE438B95A97}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>daily_courant_published</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Daily Courant</onscreen_name>
<event_text>With only a single page containing just two columns, the &quot;Daily Courant&quot; may not seem like much, but it is the first daily &quot;newspaper&quot; in the world.\n\nEdward Mallet has published this groundbreaking page from his rooms located above the White Hart Pub on Fleet Street. Consisting purely of foreign news items in order to avoid government interference, the publication carries no comment from the editor himself. As Mallet says: &quot;other people have sense enough to make reflections for themselves&quot;, this new source of daily information will surely only be the first of many &quot;newspapers&quot; to do so.</event_text>
<historical_date>1702</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{145ED08B-7B2E-4862-B428-07E047308941}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>daily_universal_published</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Times</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Two years after first publishing the Daily Universal Register, and sixteen months in Newgate for libel later, John Walter has changed his paper’s name to “The Times”.\n\nDistribution has been so good over the nine hundred and forty issues printed thus far that Walter can afford to pay more for both writers and information, giving him a distinct advantage over his competitors.\n\nThe paper currently leads the fields of politics, art, science and literature. Despite a shaky start, the future looks bright for The Times.</event_text>
<historical_date>1788</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEEAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{22A55D17-21C1-49C5-9CF8-D74A19BFEEDE}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>dark_day_new_england</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Dark Day of New England</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A great darkening of the sky has taken place over the regions of New England, causing candles to be required for lighting from midday to midnight, all the next day, and most of that night.\n\nUnsurprisingly, there are fears amongst the pious that Judgement Day is at hand, prompting this from politician Abraham Davenport &quot;I choose, for one, to meet Him face to face, No faithless servant frightened from my task, But ready when the Lord of the harvest calls; And therefore, with all reverence, I would say, Let God do His work, we will see to ours. Bring in the candles.&quot;\n\nIn actuality, the phenomenon was probably a combination of forest fires, cloud cover and thick fog.</event_text>
<historical_date>1780</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QcAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{0C66E8CF-7D49-45D7-8FAA-82F7128F1F32}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>death_penalty_rescinded</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Tuscany Abolishes Death Penalty</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A wave of insurrection, lawlessness and every other conceivable form of inhuman wickedness is certain to engulf the Grand Duchy of Tuscany following the abolition of both torture and the death penalty!\n\nThe Grand Duke, clearly a man of little constitution, has fallen under the sway of the pernicious text &quot;On Crimes and Punishments&quot; by Cesare Beccaria - which agonises about the futility of capital punishment in a most spineless manner! As such he has steadily blocked all proposed executions since coming to power.\n\nNow he has permanently enshrined his mistaken viewpoint in the laws of the land, leading no doubt to wild celebrations amongst the criminal classes.\n\nTuscany has the very dubious honour of being the first European power to ban capital punishment, sparking debate regarding the potential benefits their society might derive from this. However, the ordinary right-thinking man is left to consider this as nothing less than stark-staring lunacy - to ponder what the world is coming to and where this will all end!</event_text>
<historical_date>1786</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{371A3E52-5664-477E-A3EB-7F9D9A6876B2}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>decline_and_fall_roman_empire</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The eminent historian and sometime member of parliament Edward Gibbon has published &quot;The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire&quot;, truly his magnum opus - and the fruit of seven long years of work. The book - the first of six planned volumes - deals with the slow disintegration of the Roman Empire from 180 A.D. until 1590 A.D.\n\nHaving sold out already, the success of the first volume can be put down partly due to Gibbon’s very readable style of writing, but also that his arguments are always supported by solid reference to primary sources, notes indicating his own thought processes, and always an objective eye. Gibbon paints a picture of an empire which grew soft, self-absorbed and self-indulgent over the course of fifteen hundred years. Rome, he argues, wallowed in the material wealth secured by their forebears, was comforted by the salvation offered by their newfound Christianity and the illusory strength of the hired barbarian mercenaries in the guarding of its borders.\n\nSome readers are struck by the parallels between Gibbon’s depiction of the decline of the seemingly all-powerful Roman Empire and the similarities with the ebb and flow of the world in these supposedly more enlightened times!</event_text>
<historical_date>1776</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8Q4AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{5B30F9FD-1DA9-4A21-BDBE-756A4A922AE5}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>defoe_pillaried</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Pilloried for Satire</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Infamous failed merchant, debtor, dissenter, pamphleteer and all-round ne’er-do-well Daniel Defoe has been placed in the pillory for the crime of seditious libel following the publication of his pamphlet &quot;The Shortest Way with the Dissenters&quot;.\n\nWritten from a High Tory perspective and demanding the extermination of all religious dissenters - of which Defoe is one - the work is clearly a satire, intended to lampoon and undermine those persons in positions of authority. As such it was judged as libel likely to foster sedition, and Defoe sentenced to three days in the pillory as punishment. Quickly publishing his &quot;Hymn to the Pillory&quot;, Defoe avoided a potentially life-threatening experience and was instead pelted with nothing more injurious than flowers. The usually bloodthirsty mob also read extracts of his other literary works aloud.\n\nFurther rumours hold that since then, whilst incarcerated in a Newgate cell, Defoe has met with a government representative, and that intelligence work was the subject of their conversation.</event_text>
<historical_date>1703</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvESAAAAAAAAABQAAACQ06rxEwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEPAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{AC232DC7-655D-4B68-8A82-6FEE9EB883AE}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>AAAAABQAAACQ06rxEwAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>denmark_norway_germany_adopt_gregorian_calendar</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Gregorian Calendar</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Many Protestant nations in Europe, with the notable exception of Great Britain, have grudgingly adopted the reforms to the Julian calendar first proposed in the Papal Bull of 1582 by Pope Gregory XIII.\n\nThe new calendar seeks to correct the gradual drifting forward of the seasons and the feast of Easter under the old Julian Calendar, which was eleven days longer than its civil equivalent. The Gregorian reforms removed the extra days and inserted a leap year – an extra day every four years to further correct the previous drift.</event_text>
<historical_date>1700</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{2B6A76F8-3F5F-4377-B521-ACBFBE0AD495}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>downing_street</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Downing Street</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The First Lord of the Treasury - leader of the government of Great Britain - has moved into a new residence at Number 10, Downing Street, Westminster.\n\nThe house was until recently three buildings: a &quot;house at the back&quot; once adjoining the old Whitehall Palace, and two smaller ramshackle residences, one until recently occupied by the amusingly-named Mr Chicken, who has since been moved on - the other being the aforementioned Number 10.\n\nFollowing an extensive refit and redecoration under the guidance of prestigious architect William Kent, the buildings have truly been given a new lease of life.\n\nThe Monarch originally offered the property to the First Lord as a personal gift for services to the nation, but he has accepted only on condition that it be a gift to the office of First Lord and not himself specifically, so successive holders of the highest office would also be able to live there.</event_text>
<historical_date>1731</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{95B04F37-1853-4C27-BA58-38F7196305A2}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>dublin_gazette_published</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Dublin Gazette</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The first daily newspaper in Ireland, the Dublin Gazette, has been published for the first time. Along with the Courant in England, the newspaper represents an information milestone, giving the public easy access to national events for the first time, albeit in a government censored sedition-free form.</event_text>
<historical_date>1706</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxBQAAAJDTqvEDAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{65399866-6E61-44CD-980A-4C702D18E307}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>earl_tyburn_jig</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Tale of Earl Ferrers</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Laurence Shirley, the fourth Earl Ferrers, has been hanged for murder at Tyburn. An eccentric man with a violent temper, Ferrers&apos; wife had already secured a legal separation for cruelty, and he once kicked a servant so hard in the groin that the fellow was unable to hold water for some time afterwards.\n\nAs his estates were vested to trustees, a steward was appointed to receive rents on his behalf. Unfortunately, the man was a loyal servant of the trustees and did not act in accordance with Ferrers&apos; wishes, so having summoned him to a business meeting at his home, Ferrers shot him at point blank range.\n\nDespite offering money to the man’s relatives to keep the matter quiet, and a subsequent plea of insanity (backed up by considerable evidence!), Ferrers was found guilty and hanged at Tyburn.</event_text>
<historical_date>1760</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvETAAAAkNOq8RIAAACQ06rxFAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEQAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{F375D1E5-570B-40CF-A37B-28CC88C544B7}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>electrical_condenser</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Electrical Condenser</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Dutch physicist Pieter van Musschenbroek has demonstrated his new invention, the &quot;Leyden Jar&quot;. The device, which van Musschenbroek calls a &quot;condenser&quot;, shows that two closely spaced metal plates with a glass jar separating them are capable of condensing a high density of electrical charge and storing it in an electrical field between them - the effect being due to the insulating properties of the intervening glass.\n\nThis brilliant innovation is an important development in our striving to understand and master the mysterious force of electricity. Now what would happen if several jars were combined in parallel?</event_text>
<historical_date>1745</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8Q4AAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D8A5A686-08BD-4476-9E12-27438317B16F}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>encyclopaedia_britannica</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Encyclopaedia Britannica</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Many encyclopaedias have been published over the years, but it wasn’t until Ephraim Chambers’ two volume &quot;Cyclopedia&quot; of 1728 that publishers began to see the earning potential of such books.\n\nThe Encyclopaedia Britannica began as a reaction to the Encyclopédie of Denis Diderot, which the authors thought was merely an apocryphal translation of Chambers&apos; earlier works. Scotsmen Colin Macfarquhar, a printer and bookseller, and his partner the engraver Andrew Bell, thought that the time was right to rework the concept &quot;compiled upon a new plan&quot;.\n\nThe young William Smellie was employed as editor for the sum of two hundred pounds, and set about constructing the epic opus. The encyclopaedia was released in weekly installments between 1768 and 1771, and finally bound in a single volume later that year.\n\nAdditionally, Bell produced one hundred and sixty engravings to sit alongside the written entries, even coming under some criticism for his depictions of body parts. Whereas content was liberally borrowed from many other sources, the stylistic innovation that set the Britannica apart from similar volumes was that related topics were grouped together - rather than alphabetically - so the reader could glean a greater knowledge of a subject than ever before.</event_text>
<historical_date>1771</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEOAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{1B727BD4-D908-4A0A-9190-378E1B3FAFFA}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>encyclopedie_published</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Encyclopédie</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Originally intended as a translation of Englishman Ephraim Chambers&apos; groundbreaking &quot;Cyclopedia&quot; of 1728, work towards the Encyclopédie began in earnest in 1747, following several false starts.\n\nFinally settling on Denis Diderot and Jean Le Rond d’Alambert as editors, the Encyclopédie made use of some of the finest brains in France, including Rousseau, Voltaire, Montesquieu and Louis de Jaucourt to name but four. In total, over seventy thousand articles have been published along with over three thousand illustrations in thirty five volumes, beginning in 1751.\n\nWhereas the enlightened minds of France see the Encyclopedie as a means of breaking down superstitions and raising the level of general knowledge of the common man, there are those who see such things as dangerous sedition that takes power away from the church.\n\nAfter being officially shut down in 1759, work continued in secret under high-born patronage until completed in 1772 - the authorities secretly turning a blind eye, whilst at the same time appearing to appease the wishes of the church.</event_text>
<historical_date>1751</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{F9533AC8-8A6C-41FC-A99B-EA088050027D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>enormous_bell</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Tsar Kolokol</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Literally the &quot;Tsar of bells&quot;, the largest bell in existence has been founded from bronze by Ivan and Mikhail Motorin at the request of the Kremlin.\n\nWeighing over two hundred and sixteen tons, the bell has a diameter of twenty one and a half feet and a height of twenty feet. A number of Russian artists have decorated the bell with inscriptions and elaborate ornamentation. \n\nThe Tsar Kolokol is actually the third bell to bear this name, following two attempts in the previous one hundred years - the last of which shattered during a fire at the turn of the century.</event_text>
<historical_date>1737</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{87CB06C3-1217-4BA3-B531-1174E509DD33}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>euro_porcelain</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>European China!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The secrets of making fine porcelain or &quot;china&quot;, closely guarded for centuries in the Orient, have at long-last been discovered!\n\nThe more refined populace can now dine with an altogether better class of crockery! Porcelain is made from clay, alabaster and quartz, and as with all the most useful inventions, two men both claim responsibility for its &quot;rediscovery&quot;: physicist Ehrenfried Walther von Tschirnhaus and alchemist Johann Friedrich Bottger.\n\nHowever, would-be alchemist Bottger is known to be prone to mild exaggeration, so much so that a cash-starved monarch once detained him until he produced gold from base metals! It is unclear quite how Bottger managed to keep his head on that occasion.\n\nSober sources suggest the &quot;Meissen&quot; porcelain formula belongs to von Tschirnhaus, but the industrialisation of the process has been realised by Bottger.</event_text>
<historical_date>1708</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>[FactionBuildingExists(&quot;prussia&quot;, &quot;pottery_workshops&quot;) or FactionBuildingExists(&quot;austria&quot;, &quot;pottery_workshops&quot;)]</conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QYAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAAA0CceOEgAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6A24DAB6-8B55-4090-AA43-C61D026EB3E8}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhIAAACQ06rxEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>filth_and_naughtiness</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Trials of Edmund Curll</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A curious mixture of dismay and barely-disguised exultation has greeted the announcement of Edmund Curll’s death.\n\nPublisher Curll began his career apprenticed to a London bookseller, eventually buying the business out when his employer went bankrupt. Curll quickly put his own ideas into effect, selling cheap books for working people, and exploiting any current sensation by publishing several accounts from each and every point of view. His shop offered the widest possible range of works from religious tracts to works of &quot;adult interest&quot;; politics to poetry.\n\nDuring this time, Curll also developed a reputation for unscrupulous behaviour, shamelessly seeking publicity in whatever form he could get it - good or bad! Fraudulent medical texts were published, unauthorised copies of other publishers titles appeared and the work of other writers was plagiarised in the name of profit. In this latter respect, Curll made an enemy of Alexander Pope, and the two embarked upon a lifetime of mutual enmity and public rancour. In return for many pamphlets either stealing his work or blackening his name, Pope arranged an incident where Curll was wrapped in a blanket and beaten with cudgels by schoolboys; and on the occasion of a meeting between the two - ostensibly to bury the hatchet - Pope slipped his rival a substance causing Curll a protracted bout of vomiting!\n\nCurll’s questionable publishing practices also led to his spending time in both prison and the stocks, though typically he published a broadsheet defending his position and, rather than being pelted with the customary rocks, vegetables and ordure, was instead cheered by the mob! On his release Curll carried on his work precisely as before.\n\nHis practice of fastening on the deaths of prominent people, and being the first to publish their frequently defamatory and largely fictitious biographies has led to Curll’s description as &quot;one of the new terrors of death&quot;. Whereas his own death at 72 may be a source of comfort to many in the public eye, the average working man will no doubt miss Curll’s many graphic adult titles!</event_text>
<historical_date>1747</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8Q8AAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEEAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{680A6BBB-D8E0-4712-8B62-709A8293FF3D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>first_lord_of_lunch</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The First Lord of Lunch</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Although the concept has long existed in the Middle East, a new form of snack food has reached England!\n\nLord Sandwich, whilst engaged on important government work - or gambling inveterately, depending on which story you choose to believe - has unintentionally started a fashion of food for those busily engaged in work or play. So busy that he felt he could not leave his desk to attend luncheon, Sandwich asked a servant to bring him two rounds of bread with slices of meat as a filling.\n\nLo, the humble sandwich was born, and is now catching on all over the country - much to the bemusement of its creator!</event_text>
<historical_date>1762</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8Q8AAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{EB6AA1AB-F419-4FF5-A53F-A903498EFE01}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>first_piano</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Pianoforte</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Musician Bartolomeo Cristofori of Padua, Italy, has made a major breakthrough with the invention of his groundbreaking &quot;pianoforte&quot; - literally a harpsichord &quot;with soft and loud&quot;.\n\nAfter auditioning many more-than-suitable candidates, Cristofori was employed by the Medicis not just for his skills as a musician but also because of his analytical mind and inventive skills.\n\nIf it catches on the pianoforte will no doubt become a popular instrument for performance and composition across Europe.</event_text>
<historical_date>1709</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QYAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{BF468786-6B17-462C-BE85-3AB52D5AF5C8}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>first_pow_camp</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>First Prisoner of War Camp</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The government has purchased a forty acre plot of land at Norman Cross, just outside Peterborough.\n\nThe land has been acquired for the construction of the first dedicated permanent prisoner-of-war camp to house our enemies captured during combat for the remaining duration of a conflict. Around five hundred tradesmen have been hired to carry out the construction, and thirty wells have been sunk in order to provide drinking water for an estimated six thousand inmates.\n\nThe quarters themselves will be set out in four-unit courtyards each surrounded by a brick wall, with another brick wall surrounding the entire sixteen unit camp. The garrison and support staff&apos;s quarters are just outside the inner walls, with another brick wall and gatehouse surrounding the entire complex.</event_text>
<historical_date>1796</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{E675D9E0-5389-4B66-BD45-F17BE0DA0239}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>first_public_zoological_gardens</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>First Public Zoological Garden</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Members of the public are flocking to the &quot;Ménagerie du Jardin des Plantes&quot;, the new zoological gardens in Paris.\n\nReflecting the spirit of enquiry which dominates our modern age, the attraction offers a chance to behold a wide variety of creatures and botanical specimens at first-hand. In the past, collections of animals were the preserve of the wealthy gentleman’s private menagerie or of the travelling fair, and were exhibited merely as curiosities. A zoological garden was established on a more scientific footing in the grounds of the Schonbrunn Palace, Vienna in 1752, but was still a private concern.\n\nThe transference of the Royal Menagerie from Versailles to the existing botanical gardens in Paris represents an opportunity for scholars and laymen alike to observe a wide variety of creatures far from their native heath!</event_text>
<historical_date>1794</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvETAAAAkNOq8Q8AAACQ06rxFAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxEgAAAJDTqvERAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D2A3CF27-D7A1-46BB-97A3-949E7F2A72C2}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>first_restaurant_paris</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>First Restaurant Opens</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Paris, generally acknowledged as a leading city for European fashion and taste, has seen the opening of a new kind of eating establishment, the popularity of which may be setting a new trend that may yet equal the alehouse and inn in terms of popularity.\n\nSoup maker Monsieur Boulanger’s eatery is known as a &quot;restaurant&quot;, after the restorative soup of the same name. It differs from more traditional eating establishments in that it is intended to cater not only for travellers, but also to local residents who leave their homes to &quot;eat out&quot;. As others draw inspiration from Boulanger’s basic premise, further innovations are occurring. Already customers can sit at separate tables - rather than finding a seat at a shared table - and a variety of dishes can be ordered from a set list rather than a single dish served from a large common pot.\n\nThese new restaurants are changing public perceptions of eating outside of the home from being something done for the sake of expediency when travelling, to being a pleasurable pastime in its own right.</event_text>
<historical_date>1765</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QMAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8Q8AAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{11A48F44-DD62-4F03-BD12-FDF6BE49D1A9}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>flushing_toiletoscope</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Toilet Trap</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Watchmaker Alexander Cumming of Bond Street - also an engineer of some note - has developed an addition to the flushing toilet to &quot;trap&quot; foul air and water via a valve and a layer of fresh water from the cistern.\n\nWhen the flush is pulled the valve opens and the flush starts. It then closes automatically after the waste has been flushed away and the fresh water layer is replaced, trapping the smell and stopping it from wafting up from the pipe.</event_text>
<historical_date>1775</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{2C95341C-54B1-4A19-9D2F-A6B98F7AB289}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>flute_player_mechanical_duck</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Flute Player</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Jacques de Vaucanson has constructed a man-sized automaton that not only plays the flute, but has a repertoire of twelve songs! Whereas such creations are often viewed as mere toys, &quot;The Flute Player&quot; has been recognised as a sophisticated machine in its own right.\n\nThe Academie des Sciences are so impressed that they have agreed to display the automaton, and Monsieur Vaucanson has started work on his next machine, a mechanical tambourine player. Word has it that the inventor is also preparing to unveil his masterpiece - a mechanical animal complete with a digestion system no less! Eugh!</event_text>
<historical_date>1738</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{0AF7A9C7-EA36-479D-9EA9-8F809963A5BA}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>freemasons_america</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Freemasonry in Boston</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The London-based Grand Lodge of Freemasons has granted a charter to a new lodge in Boston, Massachusetts - thus formalising the spread of the organisation into America. Freemasonry has thrived in Britain since the formation of the Grand Lodge in 1717, which bound the previously separate masonic lodges under a common constitution.\n\nAs trade and colonisation spreads, so has freemasonry, with provincial Grand Masters representing the Grand Lodge around the world. Some voices have raised concerns over charges of nepotism and other more potentially sinister influences, but as yet the authorities seem happy for freemasonry to exist and thrive in America.\n\nCertainly its central tenets seem laudable enough: brotherly love, charity and truth. As long as its members continue to be guided only by these principles, freemasonry appears harmless enough to the majority - despite its mysterious rituals and bizarre regalia!</event_text>
<historical_date>1733</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8Q0AAAA0CceOEQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{4E0616A8-F41C-452C-9D0D-0B2BAB7F3FA3}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhEAAACQ06rxDwAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>freemasons_founded</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Freemasonry in London</onscreen_name>
<event_text>St John the Baptist’s Day - 24th June - a meeting has taken place at the Goose and Gridiron Alehouse in London between members of four London lodges of the &quot;secret&quot; society of Freemasons, forming the first Grand Lodge of London and Westminster - led by Grand Master Anthony Sayer.\n\nThe Freemasons are a fraternal organization, sharing metaphysical views such as the existence of a Supreme Being, the importance of brotherly love, and truth and charity as a route to higher standards in life.\n\nThe secrecy surrounding their methods of recognition, the eccentricity of their internal hierarchy and rituals, and the mystery surrounding the movement’s origins have led some to unease about the true nature of Freemasonry and its aims. Could it be that the assimilation of the many smaller lodges into an overarching Grand Lodge is the first act of a power play to manipulate the fortunes of common men?</event_text>
<historical_date>1717</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8Q8AAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{C95228AF-39A2-4BAF-92F1-47C7ED4B6D6D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>fruit_kills_scurvy</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>A Cure for Scurvy</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Scurvy is an appalling disease that affects sailors and soldiers whilst at sea or away from home for long periods, symptomised by spots on the legs and feet, spongey gums leading to loss of teeth, bleeding of gums and membranes, and the opening of scars thought healed. Depression and hallucination are also common symptoms.\n\nThere have been several claims over the years by European scientists stating a link between scurvy and a lack of fresh fruit and vegetables. The Royal Navy has only recently accepted this due to the efforts of one of its own surgeons, James Lind.\n\nLind has undertaken a clinical trial in order to prove his suggestion that putrefaction through scurvy can be remedied by the administration of acid supplements. In doing so, he has discovered that the sailors who recovered most satisfactorily were the ones fed on fruit - particularly citrus fruits such as lemons and limes.\n\nIt is hoped that these findings will soon be adopted as policy across all disciplines of the armed forces.</event_text>
<historical_date>1747</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>[FactionTechExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;france&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;austria&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;spain&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;prussia&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;russia&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;ottomans&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;netherlands&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;maratha&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;mughal&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;) or FactionTechExists(&quot;sweden&quot;, &quot;military_navy_lime_juice_and_sauerkraut&quot;)]</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvETAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxFAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QcAAAA0CceOFQAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{9058859F-4E9B-4184-A3E9-88DA6CC0D7BB}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhUAAACQ06rxFAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>gas_lighting</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Gas Lighting</onscreen_name>
<event_text>It is anticipated that the robbery and brutality which haunts our streets at night will soon be all but eliminated by the advent of gas lighting by Mr William Murdoch, of Messrs Boulton and Watt&apos;s Soho Foundry, Birmingham.\n\nNo doubt inspired by observations on the properties of coal gas made in the &quot;Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society&quot; - and perhaps by first hand accounts from miners and pit owners - Mr Murdoch has hit upon a system for lighting his workplace with lanterns fuelled with coal gas.\n\nSuch is the success of this scheme, first demonstrated within his own home; that plans are afoot to extend the system to the building’s exterior, and thence perhaps to every street in the land!</event_text>
<historical_date>1798</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEFAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEOAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{A483783B-6C4A-443B-863D-89E6BE3D9E23}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>gentleman_highwayman</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Gentleman Highwayman</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The notorious highwayman James MacLaine, infamous for his polite treatment of the victims of his crimes, has been caught and hanged.\n\nAlong with an accomplice, who has escaped justice, MacLaine committed over twenty robberies over a six month period, culminating in his arrest when he attempted to sell on lace stripped from a waistcoat back to the tailor who made it. Upon searching his dwellings the constable found that &quot;there were a wardrobe of clothes, three-and-twenty purses, and the celebrated blunderbuss found at his lodgings, besides a famous kept mistress&quot;.\n\nMacLaine’s trial at the Old Bailey attracted many from respectable society, as well as almost three thousand visitors during his stay at Newgate. His subsequent date at Tyburn was well attended, the writer Soame Jenyns noting that &quot;some of the brightest eyes were at this time in tears for one &apos;McLean&apos;, condemned for robbery on the highway&quot;.</event_text>
<historical_date>1750</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{4B21F46B-4E33-495A-B7E6-1D5539102E36}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>global_circulation</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Global Circulation</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A scientific paper presented to the Royal Society by Mr George Hadley has explained a meteorological phenomenon upon which much of the world’s commerce relies.\n\nThe Trade Winds are generally reliable winds blowing steadily year-round in two distinct bands to the north and south of the equator separated by a zone of variable winds running along the equator known as the &quot;Doldrums&quot;. By taking advantage of these winds, it is possible to circumnavigate the world in a westerly direction in a fairly predictable timeframe, making them ideal for use by the many trade vessels plying to and fro between hemispheres.\n\nUntil now, why the Trade Winds do not flow directly north or south has remained a mystery, since it might reasonably be expected that warm air would be forced away from the equator towards the colder poles. Hadley’s theory explains that the Earth’s rotation interferes with this process, producing winds trending towards the west and back towards the equator.</event_text>
<historical_date>1735</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>FactionTechExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;military_navy_meteorological_studies&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D4BCBA1C-95D9-4699-BE43-D59E0EC60CA0}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>guillotine_invented</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Enter Madame Guillotine!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A number of bloody executions utilising such arcane and barbarous methods as hanging, breaking on the wheel, drawing and quartering with horses, and burning at the stake have recently caused unrest amongst the common people.\n\nIn one case, the crowd attacked the executioner, set the prisoner free and burned the wheel he was to be broken upon. Dr Joseph-Ignace Guillotin has since proposed a move towards a more &quot;humane&quot; form of execution, where the gruesome spectacle is replaced by clean efficiency.\n\nAs such, he has proposed a system not unlike the Halifax Gibbet or the Scottish Maiden, where a fixed, weighted blade falls onto the neck of the victim, decapitating them relatively cleanly. Modifying this system by use of a curved blade, Antoine Louis has designed a machine commissioned to deliver decapitation with a single blow and no misses.\n\nDespite early calls for it to be named the &quot;Louison&quot; or &quot;Louisette&quot; the machine has been named &quot;Guillotine&quot;, somewhat to the chagrin of its namesake, who wasn’t involved in the design itself.</event_text>
<historical_date>1789</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{76B0B807-19C4-4ECD-9D3C-464EF82D2794}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>guiness_brewery_founded</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Guinness Brewery</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A Mr Arthur Guinness has taken a nine thousand year lease of the unused St James’s Gate Brewery in Dublin, Ireland, at the cost of £45 per annum.\n\nThere, he has begun production of a very popular dry stout beer which bears his name. Guinness stout is brewed with roasted local barley grains and water from the Wicklow Mountains to give it a characteristic taste and a dark ruby, almost black colour.\n\nIt is understood that if all goes well for Mr Guinness over the next 9,000 years, he may consider exporting a barrel or two of his excellent stout to England, and, who knows, perhaps even further afield! It might however, be too good to share.</event_text>
<historical_date>1759</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAbILpKg8AAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{0FBAC0DE-9C06-44FF-8052-EC136D75655A}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>bILpKg8AAACQ06rxDgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>gullivers_travels</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Gulliver&apos;s Travels</onscreen_name>
<event_text>From the council chamber to the taproom, Britain is a-buzz with talk of the sensational new literary work &quot;Gulliver&apos;s Travels&quot; by that satirical scribe Mr Jonathan Swift.\n\nThough ostensibly a collection of travellers tales by the eponymous Gulliver (a nautical gentleman), the book is in fact a multi-faceted work using the fantastical situations in which Gulliver finds himself to examine various aspects of the human condition, lampoon modern governments (particularly that of Britain), and to present observations about religion.\n\nOn the other hand, parts of the book can be read simply as a children’s story, and it is this wide-ranging appeal which has ensured the selling out of the first print within days of release. The work is already being hailed as a classic.</event_text>
<historical_date>1726</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{F3D7DFEA-DD11-4643-BA17-28A761C11AA5}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>halleys_comet_again</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Halley&apos;s Comet Returns</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A scientific prediction made by the former Astronomer Royal Professor Edmond Halley more than fifty years ago has been proved by the reappearance of a spectacular comet in the night sky.\n\nIn his 1705 work Synopsis Astronomia Cometicae, Professor Halley linked comet sightings from 1456, 1531, 1607, and 1682 as being one and the same astral body, returning to our skies roughly every seventy six years.\n\nThough he has been dead for more than a decade, the knowledge that the comet has now been christened &quot;Halley&apos;s Comet&quot; in his honour would no doubt be a cause of some satisfaction to the deceased gentleman.</event_text>
<historical_date>1758</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;royal_observatory&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{C9E83192-BAC8-4C91-8EA8-A4DE085C767B}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>handel_dies</key>
<picture_category>small funeral-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Handel Dies</onscreen_name>
<event_text>One week after playing organ in accompaniment to a performance of his own work &quot;The Messiah&quot;, the great composer George Friderich Handel has died of old age at seventy four, in between Good Friday and Easter Monday of 1759.\n\nAlthough normally robust in health, Handel had been blind for several years and there had been no protracted illness preceding his death. Unusually for a non-Briton, Handel has been buried at Westminster Abbey, a monument by the French sculptor Louis-Francois Roubiliac adorning his tomb in the great crypt.\n\nHandel will always be remembered as one of the great masters of music - his compositions displaying a simplicity of melody and structural clarity rarely matched by those of his contemporaries.</event_text>
<historical_date>1759</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>small funeral-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceODgAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAADQJx44OAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{BE8EB47F-984A-4E58-B82D-5BAE67526F97}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjg4AAACQ06rxDQAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>harris_list_ladies</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Harris&apos; List</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The &quot;Pimp General of All England&quot; - that objectionable blackguard Jack Harris - has published the first directory of prostitutes under his control: &quot;Harris’ List of Covent Garden Ladies&quot;.\n\nFor the first time together in a single volume, the list contains the names, physical descriptions and sexual predilections and &quot;specialities&quot; of each lady, along with their cost. The list itself sells at a steal for two shillings and sixpence. Harris’ list has in fact been written by struggling Irish poet Samuel Derrick, in order to extricate himself from debtor’s prison.\n\nAlthough Harris has given his name and official seal to the project, this is probably only for reasons of personal vanity - as the publication of a list allowing potential customers direct access to ladies may actually prevent him from plying his unpleasant trade so easily in future!</event_text>
<historical_date>1757</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;bawdy_house&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{B5EA27F7-A537-4501-8700-EB92E9F2795A}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>haydn_the_creation</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Creation</onscreen_name>
<event_text>After watching performances of Handel’s &quot;Israel in Egypt&quot; during visits to England over the preceding ten years, noted composer Joseph Haydn has unveiled his own oratorio - majestically entitled &quot;The Creation&quot; - an enormous work reflecting the composer’s own piety.\n\nTaking almost two years to complete, the deeply religious Haydn has never spent such a long time to complete a project, and following the premiere he collapsed with exhaustion, having run himself down during the composition stage.\n\nThe premiere was sponsored by a group of wealthy citizens who paid specially in order to hear The Creation’s first performance privately before it’s public debut. The chosen venue was Schwarzenberg Palace in Vienna, with admission by invite only - members of the public crowded the streets, straining to hear the piece.\n\nMany of the privileged audience members have since written positive reviews of the piece, praising its pious and uplifting qualities.</event_text>
<historical_date>1798</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{F99D1BCC-6F9A-411F-86F7-1C15AC0944BE}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>hellfire_club_english</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Hellfire Club</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Although there have been many such exclusive clubs in Britain since the Age of Reason overtook that of superstition, the Hellfire Club of Sir Francis Dashwood must surely be the most prominent. Combining in the main drunken debauchery with occasional instances of occult ritual, the club meets at the recently acquired ruins of Medmenham Abbey, near Henley-on-Thames in Oxfordshire.\n\nThere are twelve regular members in addition to Dashwood - &quot;gentlemen&quot; all - and many other regular guests in attendance also. On one occasion, after much quaffing and reprehensible behaviour, the &quot;Franciscans&quot; decided to say a prayer to the Devil. Politician John Wilkes, one of the twelve, decided to mock this aspect of their gatherings by dressing a baboon in red - complete with horns - and releasing it from a cupboard at the speaking of Dashwood’s satanic incantations. The beast proceeded to leap onto the back of Lord Sandwich, who in fear and shock exclaimed &quot;Spare me gracious Devil! Spare a wretch who was never your servant! I am but half a sinner!&quot;\n\nLet’s face it: that is not the sort of thing one can live down easily, and needless to say Sandwich and Dashwood were not amused. However, it wasn’t long before they were up to their usual debauched tricks once again. Where will it all end?</event_text>
<historical_date>1755</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QMAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{DD5F58B9-CE56-4B7C-AC8D-D160E5DF3B2A}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>hellfire_club_irish</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Irish Hellfire Club</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Scandalous rumours are filtering through from Ireland regarding the Irish branch of the Hellfire Club. This loose association of individuals were formed from the highest echelons and formed by the Earl of Rosse, and hold meetings at a variety of taverns and clubs where they revel in debauchery and occult practices - Satanism having recently reached an unfortunate degree of popularity both in England and on the continent.\n\nOne member apparently killed a dwarf purely for the craic, another shot a waiter whilst dining and had the cost added to his bill! Due to their high status these men appear untouchable and no authorities have yet moved against them, despite obviously godless behaviour from members such as Richard Chapell Whaley. Known as &quot;Burn Chapell&quot; due to his habit of riding through the countryside on Sunday mornings setting alight the many thatched roof churches, Whaley also recently injured a footman who tripped over and spilled his brandy by pouring the bottle over him and setting him alight. The subsequent fire burned down the hunting lodge used as a venue for the club’s debauched activities!\n\nWhaley’s behaviour is matched possibly only by that of his son Buck, an inveterate gambler who won ten thousand pounds by travelling to Jerusalem to play handball against the Wailing Wall, later moved to the Isle of Man with tons of earth to prove he could live abroad on Irish soil - and allegedly met the Devil himself one night in St Auden’s Church, Dublin!</event_text>
<historical_date>1796</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QQAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEDAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{94571773-1F07-4BA6-9D33-AFBA6372AFB9}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>herculaneum_excavation</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Excavation of Herculaneum</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A new academic work is shedding light on the fascinating world of antiquity. Published by Herculaneum Academy and sponsored by the authorities, &quot;Le Antichità di Ercolano Esposte&quot; is a full account of the ongoing excavation of the Roman city Herculaneum, buried under volcanic ash during the eruption of Mount Vesuvius in 79AD, the same cataclysm that destroyed Pompeii.\n\nIt is anticipated that when completed, the work will extend to some 40 volumes, complete with numerous copperplate engravings and illustrations. Detailed within are an incredible wealth of ancient paintings, bronzes, lamps, lanterns, candelabra, sculptures and other antiquities so far recovered.\n\nThough the original work was not intended for general publication, such is the level of interest that pamphlets and books of excerpts have already appeared, and the beauty of the objects is already influencing tastes in design.</event_text>
<historical_date>1738</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{F899EEC4-7916-4C16-86C6-06EA7A8A3E95}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>herschel_discovers_infrared_radiation</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Calorific Rays</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The astronomer William Herschel has presented to the Royal Society the results of his latest experiments, in which he has identified a new area of the spectrum of light that is completely imperceptible to the human eye!\n\nSir William has used a prism to refract the sun’s rays and demonstrated that a thermometer held beyond the red end of the spectrum exhibited a rise in temperature, indicating the presence of an otherwise invisible form of light. He calls this new light &quot;calorific rays&quot;.\n\nThis discovery perfectly illustrates the combination of the powers of science and an enquiring mind in revealing and explaining the hidden mysteries of our world!</event_text>
<historical_date>1800</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{BA6158B9-DA17-4B69-BD7E-0C304AE7B872}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>herschel_discovers_uranus</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>A New Planet</onscreen_name>
<event_text>German-born music teacher and amateur astronomer William Herschel has discovered a new planet in the heavens, bringing the total known number within the solar system to seven.\n\nInitially believing his observation to be a comet, Herschel contacted the Astronomer Royal, who thought it might possibly be a planet. Other astronomers soon confirmed his suspicion and within two years Herschel was invited to name his discovery. The respected French astronomer suggested the name &quot;Herschel&quot; in honour of its discoverer, but that was rejected, as was sticking to the system of using names from Greek and Roman mythology.\n\nHerschel eventually decided upon Georgium Sidus, in honour of the royal family.</event_text>
<historical_date>1781</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6E7ACF41-F25F-4269-BB47-D63875BA21D8}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>hydraulic_press</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Hydraulic Press</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The manufacturing industry has taken a giant stride forward with the announcement of a new invention by Mr Joseph Bramah, previously notable for his inventions of the &quot;beer engine&quot; and the improved water closet, amongst other equally splendid innovations.\n\nApplying the principles of fluid dynamics within a closed system as outlined by the French mathematician Pascal, Bramah has developed a powerful new hydraulic press.\n\nThe machine uses two pistons of different sizes, linked by a sealed fluid-filled system. A small force applied to the smaller piston is translated via the fluid into a far greater force on the larger piston. This force can be brought to bear on many aspects of manufacturing process and represents the dawning of a new age: that of hydraulic engineering.</event_text>
<historical_date>1795</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAABQR8O1EAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{E09E636A-31B4-450A-BD8E-711E2D4C211A}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>UEfDtRAAAACQ06rxDwAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>hydrogen_discovered</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Hydrogen Discovered</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The scientist Henry Cavendish has published a paper entitled &quot;On Factitious Airs&quot; in which he announces the discovery of a new element. Mr Cavendish writes that his &quot;Inflammable Air&quot;, liberated from mercury as a result of allowing strong acid to act upon it; is highly flammable and produces water when burned in the presence of dephlogisticated air.\n\nCavendish, a brilliant man, though painfully shy and retiring; is rumoured to be working on a calculation of the composition of the Earth’s atmosphere, amongst many other wide-ranging studies.\n\nHe may choose to share his findings with his associates at the Royal Society, or then again, he may not.</event_text>
<historical_date>1766</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{AAD14486-ACD2-4804-822D-5EA49D012696}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>irish_code_duello</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Code Duello</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A code to govern the practice of dueling amongst gentlemen has been adopted  for general use throughout Ireland, following the Clonmel Summer Assizes.\n\nAlthough essentially similar to the French Renaissance code, it is updated particularly for the use of firearms, which are considered far more deadly than swords. As such, provision is made for gentlemen to apologise for their offences, bring seconds to mediate the duel, and give starting signals.\n\nFiring into the air in order to end the duel without harming a friend is now banned by the code, as fatal accidents had become a common occurrence.</event_text>
<historical_date>1777</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBQAAAJDTqvEIAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEGAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{0E47A485-9A92-422C-AE63-116A70352424}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QkAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>isle_of_man</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Isle of Man</onscreen_name>
<event_text>For some considerable time following the death of Lord Derby, the British government has been manouvering towards revestment of the Isle of Man as a British possession.\n\nThe new Baroness Strange and Duchess of Atholl has decided to sell her family&apos;s interest in the Isle of Man to the government, ending almost eight hundred years of feudal rule.\n\nThe Lord of Mann will now automatically be the British head of state, and Britain has gained the power to levy and collect taxes on the island. This effectively starves the Manx government - the Tynwald - of money and power. No doubt this is not the end of the matter.</event_text>
<historical_date>1765</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{5595F44F-671D-4C85-AC2C-D3105132A4B9}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>jack_sheppard_hanged</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Tale of Jack Sheppard</onscreen_name>
<event_text>After leading the thief-takers a merry dance for over two years the robber and burglar &quot;Gentleman Jack&quot; Sheppard has danced his last - and the Tyburn Jig no less!\n\nFollowing five arrests and four sensational escapes, the rogue was finally captured and held in the Middle Stone Room at the very centre of Newgate, where he was constantly observed and loaded down with three hundred pounds of weights to ensure he remained in captivity. Such was the talk of Sheppard in society circles that his gaolers were able to charge a full four shillings to see him.\n\nSheppard refused to inform on his associates in return for a more lenient sentence, and despite petitions for the death sentence to be commuted to transportation for life, it was passed on 10th November. Unfortunately the slight build that had aided so many of his escapes made Sheppard&apos;s hanging a slow and painful strangulation. After fifteen minutes Jack Sheppard&apos;s corpse was cut down, leading to a surge amongst the crowd, who feared his body would be taken for dissection.\n\nMauled and mutilated, his corpse was later recovered and buried at St Martin-in-the-Fields.</event_text>
<historical_date>1724</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvERAAAAkNOq8RAAAACQ06rxEgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEOAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6C3E4B6A-B64D-49DA-81E8-731CC8BA3174}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RIAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>jamesons_distillery</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Jameson&apos;s Whiskey</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Having recently acquired the Bow Street distillery in Dublin, Scotsman John Jameson has begun production of an Irish whiskey.\n\nMade using the latest industrial production methods, Jameson’s whiskey is triple-distilled, as opposed to traditional scotch which is double-distilled. Other differences lie in the types of barley used by Jameson and that this barley is roasted over Kilkenny Anthracite coal fires, rather than the Scottish method which uses peat fuel.\n\nWhatever the differences regarding the way it is produced, Jameson&apos;s lives up to the ancient Gaelic term for whiskey: &quot;uisce beatha&quot;, or the &quot;water of life&quot;!</event_text>
<historical_date>1780</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{C08212E7-186C-421C-AD02-271F5737AEC7}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>jonathan_wild_swings</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Thief-Taker General</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The man long thought to be the leading officer of the law, the self-styled &quot;Thief-Taker General&quot; - Jonathan Wild - has been revealed to be no better than the common criminals he sought to apprehend.\n\nRunning a network of thieves bolstered by blackmail through fear of the gallows, Wild waited for crimes to be reported before returning stolen items and claiming any rewards - the profits of which were split unfavourably with his &quot;agents&quot;. Any one of them who complained about Wild’s unfair policy would be handed over to be hanged as thieves, as would any known thief refusing to co-operate with his policy and any rivals who might reveal the true nature of his activities to the authorities. Wild was responsible for the executions of over sixty thieves due to his actions, and provided the Privy Council with advice resulting in a one hundred pound increase for turning in thieves.\n\nAfter constructing a façade of heroism via clever manipulation of the press, Wild came unstuck when he took part in a violent gaol break for one of his gang members. Finding himself in Newgate, Wild then fell foul a plan by his own agents to rid themselves of him once and for all. Many of them gave evidence against him, revealing all aspects of his dastardly business practices, and he was sentenced to death.\n\nWhen Wild’s day at the Tyburn Tree came he became terribly afraid, and took a large quantity of the opiate laudanum in an attempt to kill himself. Although he didn&apos;t die, Wild fell into a coma and was hanged in this state on the morning of 24th May, to much rejoicing from the large crowd gathered to see his execution.</event_text>
<historical_date>1725</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QkAAAA0CceODwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{A6B03E04-6D85-46E3-8423-2090E3552078}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjg8AAACQ06rxDgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>kidd_hanged</key>
<picture_category>pirates afterloose.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Captain Kidd</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The notorious buccaneer William Kidd has finally been brought to justice on five counts of piracy and murder!\n\nUnfortunately, miscalculations on the part of the hangman meant Kidd had to be hanged a second time as his body weight broke the first rope, but now his gibbet swings in the breeze overlooking the Thames - an example to would-be pirates everywhere! Despite this, there remain some who mutter darkly that Kidd&apos;s honour remains intact - that he is innocent and that his fate was sealed when he tangled with the Machiavellian men of the East India Company.\n\nWe may never know for sure where the truth lies, as we may never be certain where Kidd&apos;s fabled hoard of priceless treasure is buried.</event_text>
<historical_date>1701</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>pirates afterloose.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceODgAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAADQJx44NAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{1B2A981B-AAF0-4D69-96AB-90A8C4E1BCD4}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjg4AAACQ06rxDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>kinetic_gas_theory</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Kinetic Theory of Gases</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A bold new theory on the nature of gases has been hypothesised by the physicist and mathematician Daniel Bernoulli.\n\nIn his work &quot;Hydrodynamica&quot;, the Dutch-born academic outlines a &quot;kinetic theory of gases&quot;, overturning Sir Isaac Newton&apos;s theory that gas pressure is derived from static repulsion between its molecules and suggesting instead that it is caused by the frequency of collisions of gas molecules which are in fact moving in every conceivable direction. By extension, heat is derived from the kinetic energy of gas molecules stimulated into rapid motion by a release of energy into the system.\n\nThis new understanding will doubtless aid the researches of other scientists, leading to many practical advances as yet unforeseen.</event_text>
<historical_date>1738</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8Q4AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{FC8E85B2-87D3-41C7-8107-894F5DE46354}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>last_jig_at_the_tyburn_tree</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Last Jig at Tyburn</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Tyburn has been a place of execution in London since 1196, and the terrible Tyburn Tree - three eighteen-foot wooden legs supporting nine-foot crossbeams arranged in a triangular shape - was in place and use from 1571 to 1759. The design of the Tyburn Tree made it possible to execute many criminals at once, the record being twenty four hanged simultaneously in 1649.\n\nStraddling the roadway at the junction of Edgware Road and Bayswater Road at the edge of Hyde Park, the gallows served as a grim reminder to any potential wrongdoers of the power of law in Britain, attracting large crowds whenever there was a hanging day. The tree was eventually removed in 1759, as it was blocking the highway; and a smaller mobile gallows has been used ever since.\n\nNow Tyburn&apos;s time as a place of execution is past, as its last victim - highwayman John Austin - has been hanged. As the procession from Newgate has become more and more difficult to manage - with escape attempts, rescues, and sometimes even premature killings a common spectacle - the authorities have decreed that in future condemned prisoners will be hanged outside the prison walls instead.</event_text>
<historical_date>1783</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvESAAAAkNOq8REAAACQ06rxEwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEPAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{9ABAA81F-8A01-43F0-BEDF-E974D89C132C}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>lavoisier_discovers_oxygen</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Oxygen Discovered</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Frenchman Antoine-Laurent de Lavoisier has amazed the scientific world with revelations published in his &quot;Sur la Combustion en General&quot;.\n\nLavoisier conducted experiments inspired by the work of British scientist Joseph Priestley, who announced his discovery of &quot;dephlogisticated air&quot; three years prior. However, Lavoisier&apos;s concludes that the Phlogiston Theory of Combustion (postulating that all things are comprised of two types of matter: the true &quot;dephlogistic&quot; substance, and another &quot;phlogistic&quot; part given off when the substance is burnt) is in fact entirely incorrect.\n\nMore astounding still, the nobleman&apos;s investigations have proved that Priestley&apos;s dephlogisticated air is an entirely new element,  in fact comprising part of the air we breathe. Lavoisier has begun to refer to this &quot;vital&quot; air as &quot;oxygen&quot;.</event_text>
<historical_date>1774</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QMAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{79E00B5D-C35E-42DE-AB05-415599330BB4}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>lightning_rod_lesson</key>
<picture_category>disaster_eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Explosion in Brescia</onscreen_name>
<event_text>An explosion in Brescia in northern Italy has caused almost one sixth of the city to be destroyed.\n\nAs thunder and lightning are seen as tokens of God&apos;s displeasure, the clerics in authority had refused to have a heretical lightning rod fitted to the steeple. Then the Church of San Nazaro was struck by lightning, igniting the two hundred thousand pounds of gunpowder stored there, causing the aforementioned explosion and killing around three thousand people.\n\nThe clerics have since agreed to fit a lightning rod, but oddly their stance on the storage of high explosives within the church remains unchanged.</event_text>
<historical_date>1769</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>disaster_eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{8AB3C9B3-68AB-43B6-A368-BE7B5E2515A7}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>lions_extinct_libya</key>
<picture_category>culture-otoman.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Lions Extinct in Libya</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The mountains of Tripoli, North Africa, no longer echo with the terrifying roar of the Barbary Lion as they are now believed to be extinct there.\n\nThese imposing predators, easily more than twice the weight of two large men, made the sparse mountain woodlands their home, preying on wild sheep and deer as well as the livestock of local Arab herders. As such, they came into conflict with the human population, and, coupled with the destruction of the lions’ natural habitat - and that of their prey by the gradually increasing cultivation of the land - put yet further pressure on the lion population.\n\nIt is not known whether the last examples were wiped out by hunters, starvation or disease - but the actions of mankind have certainly played a great part in the lions’ extinction.</event_text>
<historical_date>1700</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-otoman.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8Q4AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{C6E32AD6-04AB-474E-ABEE-495B9BB01C78}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>london_monster</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The London Monster</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A man who terrorized London society by following well-to-do ladies and stabbing them in the buttocks has been dubbed &quot;The Monster&quot; by the press of London.\n\nMore than fifty attacks were reported over a period of two years, many women having been left with torn clothing and knife wounds. Typically the attacks also attracted those who seek attention, with many claiming to have been stalked or struck by the monster. As a result descriptions of the man and his methods varied greatly.\n\nFollowing a number of false accusations some young men formed a &quot;No Monster Club&quot;, with badges to show that they were not the monster and to put women at ease. Finally Rhynwick Williams was arrested, after a woman identified him as the man who attacked her. The fact that Williams had alibis for many of the attacks seems to have been ignored in the race to convict somebody, and he was charged with &quot;defacing clothing&quot;, a crime that carries a heavier penalty than attempted murder. Following a farcical trial and retrial, Williams was convicted and sentenced to six years in prison.\n\nSince then, reports of attacks have reduced in number but haven’t stopped entirely, leading many to wonder if the right man is locked up in Newgate.</event_text>
<historical_date>1790</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{EEB55916-9ED5-48FF-AAB9-404C9AA7F9F7}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>longman_founded</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Longman Publishing</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Enterprising Bristollian Thomas Longman, having served an apprenticeship under London bookseller John Osborn, has embarked upon an exciting commercial venture after buying out the two bookshops of Mr William Taylor of Paternoster Row and founding his own Longman Publishing in their place.\n\nMr Osborn, also his father-in-law, is Longman’s partner in the business. It would seem that acquiring the business of Mr Taylor was a shrewd investment, since they have also acquired the rights to Daniel Defoe’s bestseller &quot;Robinson Crusoe&quot; along with the stock and properties. With such firm foundations, the story of Longman Publishing seems set to be a long and successful one!</event_text>
<historical_date>1724</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QkAAAA0CceODwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{DF8CEBB3-A146-4393-BAF4-1C83F6D8E9FC}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjg8AAACQ06rxDgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>loves_of_mars_and_venus</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Loves of Mars and Venus</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A performance by the dancer and choreographer John Weaver has heralded the introduction of a new dance variant to Britain.\n\nIn his &quot;Loves of Mars and Venus&quot;, the author of &quot;A Collection of Ball dances used at Court&quot; and &quot;A Small Treatise of Time and Cadence in Dancing&quot; uses a wide variety of gestures and movement to depict a classical storyline without any use of the spoken word whatsoever. Their dance to convey such narrative and emotion is a style known as &quot;ballet&quot; - the French word for &quot;beautiful dance&quot;. Prior to this, dance performances have been more a source of amusement than a serious art-form, with Weaver himself known for more comedic styles such as pantomime.\n\nHowever, the obvious connections between ballet and the more accepted forms of artistic expression such as drama, music and literature are such that it is rapidly coming to be seen as a very serious matter.</event_text>
<historical_date>1717</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;conservatorium&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{A260A680-5D1D-4376-BAF9-D949D840BF63}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>lucky_lucky_fellow</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>A Pickle for the Knowing Ones</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Ludicrously fortunate American businessman Timothy Dexter has published an account of his amazing life, despite never learning to spell.\n\nDexter never went to  school, started by labouring on farms from the age of eight, and moved on to an apprenticeship as a leather dresser when he was sixteen. His career being successful, Dexter married and bought a large house before investing in European currencies when their value was low, subsequently making a fortune when their value increased. Investing the money in the construction of two ships, he started a business exporting goods to the West Indies and Europe.\n\nSome of his bizarrely profitable lines were warming pans and stray cats to the Caribbean, coal to Newcastle, bibles to the East Indies, and mittens to Siberia! Dexter spent these profits on a larger house in New Hampshire and hired staff members, including his own personal idiot and poet laureate.\n\nNow Timothy Dexter’s bizarre life has been recorded in his autobiography &quot;A Pickle for the Knowing Ones or Plain Truth in a Homespun Dress&quot;, which must surely be a first as it contains no punctuation whatsoever, with capital letters strewn about randomly.\n\nGiving it away free at first, Dexter has since realised the potential of his &quot;littel book&quot;, and begun to improve it. The second edition contains an extra page containing all the punctuation marks known to him, for readers to &quot;peper and solt it as thay plese&quot;. Further editions are planned!</event_text>
<historical_date>1798</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6B5618DB-0A9B-406D-8D78-B1732E0DEA30}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>lunar_society</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Lunar Society</onscreen_name>
<event_text>After meeting for ten years for dinner and conversation on industrial and scientific matters, the Lunar Circle has gradually grown in size - now becoming the Lunar Society. The group, who meet in Birmingham, are so called as their gatherings are always held on the nearest Monday to a full moon, the logic being that the journey home is better lit and therefore safer than on other nights.\n\nConsisting of a group of remarkable polymaths covering all manner of technical and theoretical disciplines, the Lunar Society are second in stature only to the Royal Society, and see themselves as a revolutionary committee for the industrial age. They postulate radical scientific ideas, and debate them for hours in a civilised manner over a decent meal, with a view to changing and improving the world for all, forever.\n\nOne of the recurring themes of Lunar Society discussions is how to efficiently increase production capacity, as the members believe that an increase in that area would assist in achieving &quot;material decency for all&quot; in a Britain that currently boasts a grossly unfair distribution of wealth. These are radical ideas indeed within the current social order, and they may yet take hundreds of years to fully realise.</event_text>
<historical_date>1775</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;royal_academy&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{656A78EB-3A1F-444A-9138-AB05D347BD80}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>marriage_act</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>New British Marriage Act</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A new Marriage Act has been put through parliament and entered into law.\n\nFrom now on, formal church ceremonies are required, putting an end to the many common law marriages in Britain. There must also be witnesses present who must add their signatures to the certificate, in addition to the signature of the minister performing the marriage.\n\nAn age of consent has also been introduced, meaning participants under twenty one years old must seek the consent of their parents; and marriages between males aged under fourteen and females aged under twelve years are banned altogether, regardless of parental consent.\n\nChildren of marriages that do not meet all these requirements may not inherit.</event_text>
<historical_date>1754</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QMAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{28C4A07B-66BC-486B-A144-2216DDD9A7DE}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>masked_man_dies</key>
<picture_category>small funeral-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Masked Prisoner Dies</onscreen_name>
<event_text>At the Bastille in Paris, a mysterious prisoner has died after over thirty years in captivity.\n\nDebate has raged concerning the identity of the man, buried as &quot;Marchioly&quot;, but who many believe was the twin brother of the King of France! Rumours continue to persist as official correspondence refers to the man by a different name, &quot;Dauger&quot;.\n\nIt also reveals that he was allowed contact with some prisoners, but not those who may have known him before his incarceration and could reveal his identity. Adding further to the intrigue, the prisoner was moved whenever the governor was reassigned, and always wore a black velvet or iron mask to conceal his face during transportation.\n\nHis true identity may never be known, but it seems likely that the prisoner was a Marshal of France, fallen from favour - but still the chattering classes ask: just who was this masked man, and could he have been the rightful King?</event_text>
<historical_date>1703</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>small funeral-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceODAAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QYAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAADQJx44MAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{7AA1E7AB-7DC0-43F6-AF15-6DC21623DDDF}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjgwAAACQ06rxCwAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>maudsleys_precision_lathe</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Precision Lathe</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The era of the craftsman is dead! Henry Maudsley, a blacksmith and toolmaker, has developed a new kind of lathe which eschews good old-fashioned craftsmanship in favour of mere precision!\n\nUp until now, lathes have worked by the operator holding the cutting tool against the spinning material in order to work it. This is an acquired skill and produces individual pieces, with no two exactly alike.\n\nMaudsley, an employee of the celebrated hydraulic engineer Joseph Bramah, has produced a sliding tool holder fixed to the lathe itself which produces identical pieces time after time with only a modicum of operator ability.\n\nWhilst there may be misgivings about this diminution in the importance of the operator’s skill, in reality the precision lathe requires a different, equally learnable skill to operate it well, and there are many more advantages to its use.</event_text>
<historical_date>1797</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QMAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{909EF147-BDC3-40AA-B7BA-1E47F7BADB1D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>mercury_thermometer</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Mercury Thermometer</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A new member of the Royal Society, Daniel Gabriel Fahrenheit, has demonstrated a new kind of thermometer - capable of measuring a wider range of temperatures than previous designs.\n\nAfter the early death of his parents from mushroom poisoning, Fahrenheit worked briefly as a merchant, trained as a glassblower and maintained a keen interest in scientific matters. He eventually settled in The Hague, where he now produces precision scientific instruments such as barometers and thermometers.\n\nAs mercury is less volatile than alcohol, it is thus able to measure higher temperatures, and has a high coefficient of expansion ideal for use in thermometers, Fahrenheit hit upon the idea of filling his thermometers with mercury. He then needed to devise a suitable scale to use with his invention for recording temperatures, modestly naming it after himself. Of course it’ll never catch on.</event_text>
<historical_date>1724</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;royal_academy&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QcAAAAAAAAADwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{73A4A9FD-83AD-4928-ACE6-846EDBDD4526}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>AAAAAA8AAACQ06rxDgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>messiers_objects</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Messier&apos;s Objects</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Astronomer Charles Messier has published the latest edition of his catalogue of deep sky objects - stars, galaxies, clusters and nebulae.\n\nKnown as &quot;Messier’s Objects&quot;, the culmination of thirty years of observations by Messier and his assistant Pierre Méchain; the catalogue is a useful guide for astronomers everywhere to distinguish comets from fixed objects.\n\nTo date, one hundred and four objects have been identified, each one catalogued and given a number preceded by the letter &quot;M&quot; for reference purposes.</event_text>
<historical_date>1781</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{EE03F7D2-D12A-4AB1-9A5E-6C31E664538F}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>meteorite_wold_newton</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Meteorite Falls in Yorkshire!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A falling star has struck the Earth at 3 o&apos;clock on 13th December, not far from the village of Wold Newton.\n\nThis proves conclusively that extraterrestrial bodies exist, and examination by naturalist James Sowerby has confirmed that it is made of rock exactly like that found terrestrially.\n\nThe Wold Newton Meteorite is the first of its kind to fall and be observed in Britain.</event_text>
<historical_date>1795</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D3068CDA-BA0B-414D-B330-89AA7FFBE0F8}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>michell_blackholes</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>A Dark Star</onscreen_name>
<event_text>In a letter published by the Royal Society, geologist and natural philosopher John Michell has suggested the existence of a stellar phenomenon possessing the most extraordinary of properties. An object of such concentrated mass that even light itself would be unable to escape its gravitational field thus might be termed a &quot;dark star&quot; or even &quot;black hole&quot;.\n\nSince light is trapped within them these &quot;dark stars&quot; are effectively invisible, but Michell suggests that observing the motion of nearby stars affected by them would provide clues as to their location.\n\nSadly, no instruments capable of measuring all this yet exist due to technical restraints, but Michell hopes his ideas might eventually be tested through experiments in future years.</event_text>
<historical_date>1784</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;royal_academy&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{69AD069E-6246-4DA0-A1A1-837CCCDD2A25}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>mohocks_abound</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Mohock Terror</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The latest in a stream of street gangs terrorising London in recent years has come to prominence.\n\nLike their predecessors the &quot;Muns&quot;, &quot;Hectors&quot;, &quot;Scourers&quot; and &quot;Nickers&quot;, this gang of vicious ruffians - known as the &quot;Young Bloods&quot; or &quot;Mohocks&quot; (a crude interpretation of the Native American Mohawk tribe) is running amok in the streets, attacking both men and women with acts of indiscriminate and brutal violence. Unusually in this case, men are being attacked with knives - sometimes losing fingers, hands or noses - whereas women are being sexually assaulted, but no one is being robbed in the process.\n\nIt is possible by their methods that the Mohocks are wealthy young gentlemen with no need to steal, but with the insatiable thirst for the excitement of violence. The authorities have rightly fixed a bounty of one hundred pounds for the gang’s capture.</event_text>
<historical_date>1712</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{C76ECE4B-FC05-41A7-9993-4DD69AFA580D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>montgolfier_balloon</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Hot-air Balloon</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Paper-makers Joseph-Michel and Jacques-Etienne Montgolfier of Annonay have constructed a contraption to enable manned flight using hot air channelled into a large taffeta cloth bag.\n\nDuring the first test flight, the brothers lost control of the &quot;balloon&quot;, which floated over a mile before crashing. It was then destroyed by some bemused onlookers, presumably under the premise that they were preventing an invasion by the dreaded Moon people. The Montgolfiers then decided on a public demonstration, so a new balloon was constructed of sack-cloth lined with paper. This time the flight took ten minutes and covered a similar distance as before.\n\nNow Etienne took a third balloon to Paris for further demonstration. Named &quot;Aerostat Reveillon&quot; after the brothers’ collaborator Jean-Baptiste Reveillon - this time the carrying animals in a basket attachment. A chicken, a duck and a sheep were the lucky voyagers, travelling over two miles in an eight minute flight from Versaille. Despite evidence that the structure was unstable, the animals survived the journey safely - in fact the sheep wasn&apos;t even aware a journey had taken place!\n\nThe fourth balloon was even larger and designed to carry people, so a doctor and an army officer volunteered for the flight, covering nine miles and only landing when the fire began to ignite the balloon&apos;s paper lining. Plans are now afoot to develop the balloons for military purposes.</event_text>
<historical_date>1783</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8Q4AAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{89FD0DD8-7082-4A48-A62D-6181E87CEF1B}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>moscow_news</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Moscow News</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The presses of the University of Moscow have printed the first edition of a new newspaper: The Moscow News.\n\nThe weekly publication has a circulation of six hundred and features an informative mix of articles and announcements, mainly by university professors to be digested by their colleagues.\n\nUnlike its many western counterparts, there is no opinion or satire to be found within its pages - possibly through fear of punishment from a monarchy that keeps a tighter rein on the information readily available to their common populace.</event_text>
<historical_date>1756</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionGovernmentType(&quot;gov_absolute_monarchy&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{29FA4176-B1BC-42CE-9C0A-D98644B8ACD8}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>mozart_dies</key>
<picture_category>small funeral-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Mozart Dies</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, surely the youngest of the great composers, has died at the comparatively tender age of thirty five.\n\nTaken ill whilst premiering his latest work in Prague, his hands and feet had swelled in size, and by the time Mozart had reached his home he had begun vomiting copiously. Still able to continue with his work, Mozart managed to complete his &quot;Clarinet Concerto&quot;, the &quot;Little Masonic Cantata&quot; and even furthered his &quot;Requiem&quot; somewhat before becoming overcome by the disease in November. Throughout that month his body continued to swell up - the swelling soon joined by pain and vomiting - to the stage where it was not possible for Mozart to move without assistance, and he essentially became bed-ridden from that point onwards.\n\nMozart passed away on 5th December with his wife and family around him. Although the cause of the illness is not definitely known, it is suspected that the composer had Rheumatoid Fever - he had previously suffered from Rheumatism - and had not been poisoned by a rival as Mozart himself suspected.</event_text>
<historical_date>1791</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>small funeral-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceODwAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QkAAABQR8O1EAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAADQJx44PAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{2D1964E5-6FC4-492F-8A6A-D55997BD3F65}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>UEfDtRAAAAA0CceODwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA=
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>mozart_eine_kleine_nachtmusik</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Eine Kleine Nachtmusik</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Taking a break from the composition of the opera &quot;Don Giovanni&quot;, the young genius composer Mozart has produced a &quot;Serenade for Strings in G Major&quot; - also known as &quot;Eine Kleine Nachtmusik&quot; - literally &quot;A Little Serenade&quot;.\n\nAlthough written with a four or five piece chamber ensemble in mind - two violins, viola, cello and maybe double bass also - Eine Kleine Nachtmusik can also be performed with more than one musician performing each part.</event_text>
<historical_date>1787</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6E71B545-DCEC-46D2-A4F1-B9B5510A9BDD}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>mungo_park_segu</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Mungo Park and the Segu kingdom</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Long thought dead, intrepid Scots explorer Mungo Park has returned from uncharted Africa against the odds with his life and the discovery of the course of the Niger river.\n\nContracted to the African Association after returning from Sumatra - where he journeyed as a surgeon of the East India Company, Park agreed to the hazardous exploration despite the disappearance of the Association’s previous employee, Daniel Houghton - who was never seen again.\n\nReaching Africa in early 1795, Park moved north along the Gambia river towards its source, before crossing the upper basin of Senegal with only two local guides and the minimum of provisions. Whilst crossing the arid Kaarta region he was failed by his poor knowledge of Arabic and captured by Moors who imprisoned him at Ludamar for several months. Park eventually escaped with only a horse and a pocket compass - almost one year since beginning his epic journey. One month later Park finally reached the Niger at Segu. He is the first and only European to date to do so. Park then began to follow the Niger’s course down river, travelling eighty miles to Silla before a lack of resources forced him to stop. For his return to Gambia, Park decided to follow the Niger’s course as closely as possible, eventually covering and tracing the course of the river for three hundred miles before falling ill with a terrible fever.\n\nAfter several months recovering at the home of a kindly African, Park got back to his base at the British Trading Post at Pisania in June 1797. He reached Scotland in December of that year, almost three years after he originally set out.\n\nNow heralded as a national hero and having more than proved his worth as an explorer, Park has published an account of his adventures as &quot;Travels in the Interior of Africa&quot;, and is preparing for an equally dangerous return trip. This time, Park is undertaking to find the source of the Niger river, and taking a detachment of soldiers and support staff with him.</event_text>
<historical_date>1796</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{245604AF-CD25-42E8-ABF8-0098751DC8DE}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>murder_most_horrid</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Severed Head</onscreen_name>
<event_text>When a severed head was found in the Thames (and displayed on a spike at St Margaret’s churchyard in an effort to identify the unfortunate man), no one realised the full horror of the fate that had befallen him.\n\nAt least three people stepped forward to identify the man as John Hayes, a local coal merchant. When his wife Catherine was interviewed she insisted he was away on business, something his associate Mr Ashby did not believe - as he had been due to meet Hayes for business purposes and he had failed to show up. Ashby questioned Catherine himself, and when she told him that her husband had fled the country after committing a murder, he went straight to the authorities.\n\nWhen constables paid a visit to Catherine at home they found her in bed with her lodger, Thomas Billings - who later turned out also to be her illegitimate son. They were both arrested along with Thomas Wood, a friend of Billings, who soon confessed to using his butchery skills to dismember the body of John Hayes. Wood insisted that he did not kill Hayes - implicating that Catherine Hayes and Billings had committed the murder.\n\nIt soon became apparent that, unsatisfied with the quality of life that her husband had provided for her, Hayes had paid Billings and Woods to get her husband blind drunk and then Billings had hit him several times with an axe, whilst Wood dismembered the body.\n\nBy this point, the remaining body parts had been found in a pond in Marylebone Fields, and wounds on the severed head seemed consistent with an axe attack. Catherine confessed, insisting that the devil was within them and it was he that had made the trio commit murder. All three were sentenced to death - the men to hang and be gibbetted, Catherine Hayes to be burned alive at the stake for petty treason in killing her lawful husband.</event_text>
<historical_date>1725</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QUAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{9907F0A4-83FE-4559-B490-52B51446F6FD}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>new_atomic_theory</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Atomic Theory</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A new theory published by the brilliant Dalmatian scientist Roger Joseph Boscovich in his &quot;Theoria philosophiae naturalis redacta ad unicam legem virium in nalura existentium&quot; - &quot;Theory of natural philosophy derived to the single law of forces, which exist in nature&quot; - has caused great excitement within the scientific community.\n\nThis new work is an attempt by the Jesuit-educated Boscovich to better explain the structure of the universe. Boscovich’s &quot;atomic&quot; theory suggests that objects are not composed of solid, continuous matter but of prodigious numbers of point-like structures or &quot;atoms&quot;, which are indivisible as the smallest particles in existence. He further suggests that these atoms are centres of force, and that this force varies in proportion to their distance from each other.\n\nThe view this theory provides of our three dimensional world in microcosm is guaranteed to open up new vistas in human understanding, and can only serve to shed light on the &quot;bigger picture&quot;!</event_text>
<historical_date>1758</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QQAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{8F5D369F-D2D3-4455-B6F5-CDE741B9ECD1}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>new_britain_discovered</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Nova Britannia</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Captain William Dampier of HMS Roebuck has returned from a voyage of exploration in the southern latitudes, where he has been engaged in mapping several coastlines around New South Wales and the former Spanish possession of Nova Guinea.\n\nAs an experienced seaman, having circumnavigated the world during his time as a buccaneer, he found himself marooned with a shipmate on a South Sea island and escaped by building a raft - eventually returning to England with nothing but the clothes he wore and his journals.\n\nDampier successfully published his journals as &quot;New Voyage Around the World&quot;, which caught the attention of the Admiralty. They engaged his services as commander of the Roebuck exploration expedition. After successfully charting several coastlines and discovering an island now named &quot;Nova Britannia&quot; - or &quot;New Britain&quot; -  the Roebuck eventually bore up for home, unfortunately foundering on Ascension Island. Fortunately Dampier and the surviving crew were soon picked up by a passing East India Company vessel.\n\nUpon returning to Britain, Dampier&apos;s discoveries have been marred by accusations of brutality - a crew member imprisoned in Brazil returned before Dampier and blackened his name with the Admiralty. Despite protestations, Dampier has been court-martialled and stripped of his position and pay for the entire voyage. Undeterred, he has since published an account of this second circumnavigation and is actively contemplating a return to his previous buccaneering lifestyle.</event_text>
<historical_date>1700</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{9029B611-85C1-4FD8-AAAB-A283A88FAEDA}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>orrery_invented</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Orrery Invented</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The celebrated clockmaker George Graham has produced a wondrous mechanical device that accurately models the motion of the planets. With a model sun at its centre, and the planets arrayed around it on metal rods, the machine is powered by a characteristically accurate clockwork mechanism.\n\nCopies of this fascinating and beautiful machine are being produced for several persons of high status, including the Earl of Orrery - under whose patronage the project was undertaken, and in whose honour the apparatus has been named. Whereas the ancient Greeks are said to have modelled the known planets and their motions, Graham&apos;s Orrery is the first example of such a device from our modern age, including many planets of which the ancients were unaware.\n\nThe Orrery is all the more admirable in that the skill and complexity of its construction mirrors, in some small way, the infinite intricacies of the heavens, and yet serves to present these difficult concepts in a fashion readily apparent to those without an enquiring mind when it comes to matters of science.</event_text>
<historical_date>1704</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceOEQAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEDAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAADQJx44QAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{C2B8B06E-7FEB-4EE4-BAB2-9BE980B26F3B}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjhEAAACQ06rxDwAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>ottoman_press</key>
<picture_category>culture-otoman.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Printing Press</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Banned for centuries in Ottoman lands for religious reasons, the Sultan has recently relaxed the rules on the printing of Turkish or Arabic script within his empire as part of his policy of reform.\n\nThis is possibly due to fears that the western powers are moving too far ahead of the Ottomans in terms of technology. As such, the first press has been set up by Ibrahim Muteferrika - a Hungarian convert to Islam - and staffed by skilled Jewish workers who up until now have been printing exclusively in the Hebrew language.\n\nIn the past Muslim religious works were literally viewed as scriptures, so it was thought highly blasphemous to print them. The first book to run off Muteferrika’s presses is a useful Turkish-Arabic dictionary.</event_text>
<historical_date>1729</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-otoman.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvERAAAAkNOq8Q8AAACQ06rxEgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEOAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D67CBE60-35F2-4A44-8739-A65988E8CDDE}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RIAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>pants_on_fire</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Claims of Mary Toft</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Mary Tofts of Godalming has recently been the subject of no little attention following her claims to have given birth to no less than sixteen rabbits!\n\nThe apparently pregnant Mrs Tofts was weeding when she chased away two rabbits, causing her to miscarry her child. From that moment on Tofts claims that she dreamed of rabbits constantly - that the trauma had caused &quot;such a longing&quot; for a child that her pregnancy continued, eventually producing nine complete baby rabbits and the arms, legs, etc. of several others.\n\nDumbfounded, the local midwife sent letters to noted medical men from around the country, piquing the interest of several famous surgeons and anatomists sufficiently to attend. The doctors eventually proclaimed the births to be due to &quot;maternal impressions&quot; - where the experiences of the pregnant woman could directly affect the foetus within her, causing it to develop in a deformed way.\n\nAfter catching a porter smuggling a dead rabbit into Mrs Toft’s room, she was forced to admit that the whole affair had been a hoax - leaving much egg on the faces of certain until-that-moment-well-respected members of the medical profession!</event_text>
<historical_date>1726</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{4C030FBE-14FE-4379-9CCF-EB6BB8DCB473}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>petticoat_duel</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Petticoat Duel</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Following a social call to her friend Lady Almeria Braddock, a Mrs Elphinstone made a casual comment regarding her true age during conversation, and was immediately challenged to a duel in Hyde Park!\n\nPistols were selected and after each taking a shot at ten yards - the only harm from which was a sizeable hole in Lady Braddock’s hat - the ladies selected sabres and continued the challenge, despite being urged by their seconds to stop.\n\nAfter a scrape on the arm, Mrs Elphinstone apologised and the matter was put to rest with signed statements and a curtsy from both parties, their honour and friendship fully intact.</event_text>
<historical_date>1792</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{4EF392ED-A901-4022-B914-DF610B8539D6}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>piratey_bishop</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Archbishop Lancelot Blackburne</onscreen_name>
<event_text>There aren’t many fellows who can lay claim to successful careers in both the priesthood and piracy whilst busy philandering at the same time, but Lancelot Blackburne may be one of them!\n\nFollowing his education at Christchurch College, Oxford, Blackburne was ordained in 1681, and the young priest set sail for a posting in Antigua at the first opportunity - in order to escape a terminally quiet life in the shires. Blackburne’s disappointment upon finding his wages paid in sugar was enough for him to move to Nevis in the Antilles, where he served aboard a pirate vessel - as either chaplain or buccaneer - before returning to England after only a short time abroad!\n\nIn an attempt to settle down into the ecclesiastical life, Blackburne befriended elderly members of the priesthood with a view to securing pleasant accommodation for himself after their deaths, becoming Rector of Calstock and eventually sub-Dean at Exeter Cathedral.\n\nTellingly, in 1702 Blackburne was accused of adultery with the wife of the interestingly-named Mr Martyr, and evidence was produced detailing a passage between their houses constructed especially to allow the tryst to continue unobserved! Blackburne sensibly resigned from his post at this stage, but was inexplicably reinstated before long.\n\nAfter spending much of his time in London ingratiating himself with the Court in as many ways as were available to him, Blackburne was made Bishop of Exeter in 1716 and, following even greater displays of idleness and philandering, Archbishop of York in 1724.\n\nAfter this date little is heard about him of a precise nature, other than to say Archbishop  Blackburne continually failed to carry out his ecclesiastical duties, and devoted much of his time to the pleasures of the flesh. For research purposes only of course!</event_text>
<historical_date>1743</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEEAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{182B2DDA-A701-4BEF-8A06-002CB12F35CB}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>potato_mandate</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Potato Mandate</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Following disease epidemics and famine in Prussian lands, the peasantry have been instructed to grow potatoes in order to survive.\n\nLong-dismissed as a mere novelty food across Europe, the potato is in fact an abundant and nutritious source of food, a great crop that can be harvested through very little effort on the part of the planter, and of course the whole process can be turned around in half the time required to propagate the equivalent crop of wheat.\n\nThe peasants are of course unhappy about a royal mandate that literally denies them their daily bread, but the soldiers dispatched to enforce the law should go some way to improve their dispositions on the matter.</event_text>
<historical_date>1757</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{E039DF06-DD05-447C-B049-0811DF6648FB}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>preserved_in_vitriol</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Buried in Vitriol</onscreen_name>
<event_text>An extraordinary tale to make the very flesh creep has emerged in Sweden.\n\nMen working in a copper mine recently entered a long disused tunnel and found a body now proved to be that of Fet-Mals Israelsson, a miner who disappeared 42 years previous. When the body was brought to the surface, it turned as hard as rock. Notwithstanding the fact that his former fiancée still lives, the apparently petrified body has been put on display as a curiosity.\n\nHaving seen the corpse, the renowned naturalist Carl Linne has suggested that Israelsson’s body has in fact been covered and preserved in Oil of Vitriol. Since the oil is now slowly evaporating due to contact with outside air, inevitable putrefaction will now set in - there being some early signs of this already. Until this happens, the unfortunate Israelsson’s body remains on display - despite calls for his immediate burial.</event_text>
<historical_date>1719</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{86308623-5AEE-464F-89CF-571633167774}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>princeton_founded</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The College of New Jersey</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The pioneering spirit so vital for survival on the American frontier, is to be furthered by learning and a quest for knowledge, following the foundation of the College of New England in the town of Elizabeth.\n\nThe new college will provide training for Presbyterian ministers under the presidency of Mr Jonathon Dickinson, himself an active minister in the Presbyterian church. Though it has a strong Christian element at its heart, the college’s charter is unique in its statement that &quot;any person of any religious denomination whatsoever&quot; may attend.\n\nThough the first year’s students number only ten, and these attending classes in Mr Dickinson’s parlour, it is anticipated that the college will grow from strength to strength in the years to come.</event_text>
<historical_date>1746</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8Q4AAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{00319805-C292-4DB9-AEF6-02C4F25BCD15}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>prussian_census</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The First European Census</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Prussia has become the first state in Europe to conduct a census of its people.\n\nIn what must be saluted as a stunning example of almost machine-like efficiency, the authorities have systematically gathered information on population movement, births, marriages deaths, and migration statistics in order to provide an accurate count of the entire population.\n\nQuite what the Prussian people make of all this; and quite what the Prussian authorities intend to do with the information is a subject of some conjecture. No doubt taxation comes into it somewhere.</event_text>
<historical_date>1719</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D3F56B1D-E5C2-47B8-9860-C565052E8EF8}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>radical_suggestion</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Pencil Marks Erased!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Edward Nairne has made a discovery. An engineer engaged with industrial design work, Nairne accidentally picked up a piece of rubber instead of the traditional piece of stale crustless bread, and used it to erase charcoal and graphite marks from a diagram he was preparing. Finding the rubber more effective at removing pencil marks, Mr Nairne has since found that selling natural rubber erasers for three shillings per half-inch cube a most lucrative alternative to the technical draughtsmanship that previously took up his time.\n\nHe is now actively seeking ways to improve upon his discovery, as the rubber currently used crumbles and decays after a short time, making it no more durable than the bread.</event_text>
<historical_date>1770</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{9D3C60A6-28B5-4380-A2AC-875535CA1AFB}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>rakes_progress</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>A Rake&apos;s Progress</onscreen_name>
<event_text>English satirical artist William Hogarth has followed his original set of paintings with a series of eight prints detailing the life of &quot;Tom Rakewell&quot;.\n\nRakewell is a fictional rogue, who spectacularly falls from a life of privilege to one of despair in the Bedlam madhouse - via dishonourable and outrageous spending, gambling, whoring, debt and prison.\n\nHogarth intends his work to be seen as both a social commentary and cautionary tale to those who may stray from the path of morality and righteousness, so easy and tempting a path in this modern world!</event_text>
<historical_date>1735</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{00138DCE-F81F-41BB-A1FD-DC6A6FEF9942}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>reflexions_critiques</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Reflexions Critiques sur les Histoires des Anciens Peuples</onscreen_name>
<event_text>&quot;Reflexions Critiques sur les Histoires des Anciens Peuples&quot;, a newly published work by the celebrated French orientalist Etienne Fourmont, is exciting great interest in the nature of myth.\n\nThe work is very learned, seeking to establish common links between the deities and mythological figures of various civilisations. Professor Fourmont’s formidable linguistic skills have enabled him to examine the roots of words and mythical names, thereby tracing their development through various cultures and establishing commonalities. By this method he has arrived at a number of surprising conclusions, amongst them that Abraham is one and the same being with Saturn from the ancient Roman pantheon - and thus that the god Jupiter and Abraham’s son Isaac are also the same.\n\nFourmont’s reasoning, backed as it is by layer upon layer of detailed examples and etymological proofs - however tenuous - is proving very difficult to dispute. His ideas have sparked a debate on the nature of mankind that seems set to run for some time yet.</event_text>
<historical_date>1735</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{78D72D64-B232-4E11-9AA2-45C00C7255E8}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>robbie_burns</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Poems, Chiefly in the Scottish Dialect</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A book of poetry and satire penned by a simple Scottish farmer and entitled &quot;Poems, Chiefly in the Scottish Dialect&quot; has been received with a surprising degree of enthusiasm.\n\nThough having little formal education beyond that which his penniless father was able to give him, Robert Burns’ work has a direct, often humorous connection with its subject, and this rough honesty is heightened by the Scots dialect which the poet frequently employs.\n\nPrinted and published by John Wilson of Kilmarnock, the work is also known as the Kilmarnock Volume and its six hundred initial copies have long since sold out.\n\nBurns provides an insight into the peasant’s way of life in &quot;The Cotter’s Saturday Night&quot; and &quot;The Twa Dogs&quot;, whilst his &quot;To a Mouse&quot; and &quot;To a Mountain Daisy&quot; both reveal a tenderness towards the natural world and an awareness of the fragility of mortality.\n\nThough the work has received plaudits further afield, Burns’ popularity is at its strongest amongst his fellow Scots, whose pride has been stirred to see their native tongue raised to the level of noble art.</event_text>
<historical_date>1786</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8Q4AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{433F19E1-5D62-465F-9EFE-677DA8395D9C}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>robinson_crusoe_published</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Robinson Crusoe</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The writer Daniel Defoe has been catapulted to fame and public adulation following the publishing of his novel &quot;The Life and Adventures of Robinson Crusoe&quot;.\n\nThe tale is a fictional autobiography of a sailor who is marooned on a desert island for twenty eight years. After a variety of adventures the mariner returns to England, where he settles happily for the rest of his days.\n\nDefoe’s inspiration for the story may have come from the real experiences of Alexander Selkirk, himself marooned for four years on a Pacific island at the beginning of this century. However, the tale is more than just a simple adventure story. In his efforts to survive on the island, Crusoe brings enlightened thinking to bear, fortified by the Holy Bible - which is at first his only companion. When he is joined by the native Man Friday, Crusoe begins the process of bringing enlightened thought to the savage.\n\nThough a few radicals might wonder whether Friday gained anything by being thus &quot;civilised&quot;, Robinson Crusoe can be viewed as a symbolic representation of colonisation - carving out the new world from a wilderness.</event_text>
<historical_date>1717</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D86523BC-F356-4AB5-A2B5-6B7384AEBA9B}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>rosetta_stone</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Rosetta Stone</onscreen_name>
<event_text>An object of great interest has been unearthed during construction work at the Egyptian port of Rosetta. Standing over one metre high and almost as wide, the artifact is a piece of granite engraved with what appears to be a decree from a Ptolemaic-era Pharaoh in three languages.\n\nThe text appears first in classical Greek - a known language and the everyday language of the ruling Pharaoh of the time - and what appears to be two forms of ancient Egyptian Demotic and Hieroglyphic writing, both lost languages that have proved indecipherable to scholars of antiquity.\n\nApparently, during Ptolemaic rule official Pharaonic edicts and decrees were published in all three languages in order that subjects from all Egyptian sub-cultures could understand their meaning. It would appear that all the texts refer to the same decree, so it is hoped that translation of the Greek text will provide a key for translating the other languages.\n\nThe race is now on as academics from across Europe struggle to crack the code that has proved so elusive until now, but can reveal so much about the ancient world previously thought lost.</event_text>
<historical_date>1799</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QMAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{3A68C0F1-8F59-474E-9484-9A76C90E3D5B}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>rule_britannia</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Rule Britannia!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A rousing tune is on the lips of every alert British patriot following the performance of a new musical piece at the elegant country retreat of Cliveden, near Windsor. &quot;Rule, Britannia!&quot; was originally a poem by James Thomson, but has now been set to stirring music by Thomas Arne.\n\nThe performance at Cliveden comprised a masque entitled &quot;Alfred&quot; - the tale of the Medieval English king no less. The audience were so stirred by the ardent patriotism of &quot;Rule, Britannia&quot; that there was very nearly uproar! Everyone from the high to the low has been whistling or humming the melody ever since, and alehouses the length and breadth of the land are resonating to the steady bull-like roaring of the chorus &quot;Rule, Britannia! Britannia, rule the waves! Britons never, never, never shall be slaves!&quot;\n\nWhilst the patriotic sentiment is indeed an admirable thing, there are doubtless many navally-challenged rival nations in Europe and beyond to whom those words smart like a freshly made sabre-wound!</event_text>
<historical_date>1740</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;opera_house&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvESAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxFAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxEgAAAJDTqvEPAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{47842B00-C29B-4F33-9CF8-190990EC3654}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>russia_julian</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Julian Calendar</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Though to many observers time in Russia passes slowly, this year it has actually contrived to go backwards by over five and a half thousand years! For time out of mind, Russia has used an &quot;Anno Mundi&quot; calendar based on the creation of the world - as pinpointed most accurately by Panodorus of Alexandria, in antiquity. This calendar puts New Year’s Day on 1st September and holds the current year to be 7208.\n\nHowever, the Tsar has recently returned from an embassy to Europe and decreed that Russia shall henceforth adopt the Julian calendar in use there. The Julian calendar is a Roman system modelled on the tropical year, beginning on January 1st and lasting 365 days - with an extra day every fourth or &quot;leap&quot; year. In addition, the numbering of years has also been changed to the Anno Domini system - beginning from the accepted birth year of Christ.\n\nWith Russia’s prestige rising as her stature among her western allies grows, the Tsar is doing away with the complexities of converting between calendars that previously led to embarrassment on the battlefield where allies would turn up to fight weeks apart, believing they were to converge on the same date.\n\nWhereas the Tsar has made the change an official mandate across the empire, it has not yet been acknowledged by the clerics of the Orthodox faith, who continue to use the original system.</event_text>
<historical_date>1700</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvERAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxEgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEPAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{180B3DD4-7213-4359-9813-D0CBAC581908}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RIAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>saint_patrick_of_noo_yawk</key>
<picture_category>Religion_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>St Patrick&apos;s Day in New York</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Since the English made it illegal for a Roman Catholic to vote or attend parliament following the rebellion of 1641, America is home to many Irish immigrants of all kinds.\n\nThe community in New York has become so large in recent years that the St Patrick’s Day celebrations have become a real occasion!\n\nThe Crown and Thistle Tavern is the venue chosen to celebrate the day, and this year the event promises to be as large as the regular parade for the feast in Boston, Massachusetts!</event_text>
<historical_date>1756</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Religion_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{418AD970-53BF-4BF2-A09A-ACF3419FAE2D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>sausage_dictionary</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>A Dictionary of the English Language</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Essayist and all-round literary brainbox Samuel Johnson has finally published his much lauded &quot;Dictionary of the English Language&quot; to much acclaim.\n\nHis payment of fifteen hundred guineas long since spent - partially due to the work taking three times as long as intended - Johnson has been supporting himself by his regular writings in &quot;The Rambler&quot; pamphlet, and by the kind donations of monied supporters of the dictionary project. Despite the paltry level of his income, Johnson has already refused a sizeable cheque from Lord Chesterfield post-release - replying at length and objecting to his belated support.\n\nHowever, as Johnson cannot glean further wealth from the book itself - the profits belonging entirely to the publisher - he has sold a collection of his &quot;Ramblings&quot; as a single volume, and already begun a new weekly column - and both seem to be doing well by the name of the author of the great dictionary.\n\nAlthough several attempts have been made to produce a dictionary in the past, Johnson’s is the grandest in terms of the research undertaken and the quality and number of his definitions. It is also possibly the largest book of its kind ever at a staggering eighteen inches tall by twenty inches wide!</event_text>
<historical_date>1755</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8Q8AAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{A97F6795-3F84-4072-A053-C03C7A85805D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>selkirk_rescued</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Castaway Mariner Rescued</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Following an altercation with his ship’s captain, Scotsman Alexander Selkirk found himself marooned on the island of Juan Fernando.\n\nOriginally part of a Caribbean buccaneering expedition, Selkirk’s complaints about conditions and the seaworthiness of their vessel culminated in an attempt to organise a mutiny, for which the captain unceremoniously dumped him on the archipelago to fend for himself. With only a musket, a knife, a bible, some tools for building shelter, and the clothes he stood up in, Selkirk soon regretted his actions - but by that time his ship had sailed away.\n\nInitially staying on the beach for fear of attack by animals, Selkirk began by living in a cave and eating shellfish to survive. Each day he watched for ships that might rescue him, and gradually sank into a paranoid depression as none appeared.\n\nHe eventually abandoned his cave when mating sealions took over the beach, moving inland. Almost straight away things improved for him. His food supply became more varied, as wild goats roamed the countryside, edible roots were abundant in the soil, and there were berries from bushes also. Selkirk soon found that his natural cunning and resourcefulness served him well in his island home - rats that gnawed at him were a genuine problem until he made friends and camped with feral cats.\n\nUsing his tools to build wooden huts, Selkirk hunted goats with his musket until his gunpowder ran out, then had to learn to chase his prey and kill them with his knife alone. At one point he fell off a cliff whilst hunting, knocked himself out for a while and woke to find - instead of a broken back - that his fall had been broken by the carcass of the goat he was chasing.\n\nIn order to keep a grasp on the language he had no cause to use, Selkirk read the bible aloud. He also found it calmed his at-times-frantic emotional state. Over the course of four years only two ships sailed within rescue distance, but he hid, as they were Spanish vessels and he feared torture and death at their hands.\n\nFinally in early February 1709 British privateers commanded by Woodes Rogers sailed into the harbour. Selkirk was overcome with joy, and having made contact set about catching goats to share with his rescuers. Rogers happily made Selkirk his mate and took him off the island.</event_text>
<historical_date>1709</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{FEC40DDA-B8CF-4610-A36F-72C5595AD775}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>senefelder_lithography</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Lithography</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Johann Alois Senefelder, an actor and playwright from Austria, has developed a new technique that will greatly aid the process of printing.\n\nHaving experienced problems with the printing of one of his plays that caused him to get into debt, Senefelder began to experiment with ways of simplifying the process and printing his works himself. The established method of printing involves preparing a raised metal plate or stone tablet to convey the ink to the page, with preparation being both costly and time-consuming.\n\nThe new method uses an ink, acid and salt mixture - the ink adhering to a wet, raised limestone surface, whilst the acid and salt washes the rest of the plate clean. The reduced wear occurring on such flat printing plates allows for longer, more efficient print runs.\n\nAs Senefelder has used a local limestone to form his plates, the process has become known as lithography, after &quot;lithos&quot;, the Greek word for stone.</event_text>
<historical_date>1798</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8Q4AAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{1A0B5A31-C250-4AFC-9580-D43DA5256AB0}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>shakespeare_festival</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Much Ado About Nothing!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The inaugural Shakespeare Jubilee has taken place in Stratford-upon-Avon to celebrate the playwright’s two hundredth anniversary.\n\nOrganised by the famous actor David Garrick - also a theatre manager and former pupil and friend of Dr Samuel Johnson - the festival has been the focus of much frenzied excitement. Fancy dress balls, salutes by cannon, serenades, recitations, poems and even a Shakespearean Cup horserace have featured, whilst commemorative medals have also been struck, pageants laid on, and fireworks displayed.\n\nAs well as promoting a love of Shakespeare, Garrick has done well for himself financially-speaking, selling special editions of Shakespeare’s plays at two shillings each - no doubt seen as a fair way to recover his expenditure from repairing Stratford Town Hall!\n\nOddly though, none of the Bard’s actual plays were performed during the celebrations, though Garrick is working on a much-anticipated play entitled &quot;The Jubilee&quot; for London audiences unable to attend the main event. Above all, Garrick has pulled off a massive public relations coup, placing not just Shakespeare, but also himself, firmly in the public eye for some time to come.</event_text>
<historical_date>1769</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;theatre&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8Q4AAACQ06rxEgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{E1CF192C-AEE1-4528-A49E-DC203B32C83D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RIAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>smallpox_euro_inoculation</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Smallpox Inoculation</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Since the dawn of time smallpox has stalked mankind, killing one in three of those infected, and leaving many survivors permanently scarred, impotent or even blinded. Its victims in this century alone number countless millions.\n\nThe shadow of death has now receded from Europe in the light of wisdom from the east. Though originally treated with skepticism by the west, rumours that a preventative method used in India, China, parts of Africa, and now the Ottoman Empire have finally been proved correct. The process involves grinding the scabs from a smallpox victim&apos;s skin to a powder then blowing them up the recipient’s nose, or rubbing infected pus into a small skin lesion. Having endured a mild form of the disease, the patient will then enjoy immunity (or, just occasionally, an agonising death).\n\nDespite some early reluctance, the process is now gaining in popularity in Europe. In Britain for instance, the royal family have all been inoculated. Any initial squeamishness they may have felt was overcome by the simple expedient of compelling several convicts to receive the treatment and observing, none of them having died, that it was probably safe to proceed.</event_text>
<historical_date>1701</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QQAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{85FA52DC-3BD9-4A2D-8A5E-B28D97860775}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>smallpox_jenner_vaccination</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Smallpox Vaccination</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Dr Edward Jenner has struck a mighty blow against one of mankind’s greatest enemies: the deadly disease known as Smallpox!\n\nAs a boy, Jenner was apprenticed to a doctor and noticed that farm workers who contracted cowpox never seemed to develop the human form of the disease. Many years later, having studied medicine and set up his own practice, Jenner resumed his study of the relationship between the two diseases.\n\nWhereas inoculation has the disadvantage of requiring access to a smallpox victim, Jenner hopes to achieve similar results from the harvesting scabs from less-harmful cowpox and keeping a supply available to &quot;vaccinate&quot; people in times when the disease does not have a strong grip - thereby ensuring it cannot get one.\n\nIn order to test his &quot;vaccine&quot;, Jenner recently took the opportunity to use a milkmaid with cowpox to inoculate the son of his gardener against smallpox. Taking an enormous risk, Jenner then attempted to infect the boy with deadly smallpox, but happily this proved to be impossible!\n\nHaving presented his results to the Royal Society, Jenner is now engaged in a series of tests on voluntary subjects in order to confirm his results.</event_text>
<historical_date>1796</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QQAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QMAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{E20AB3F3-3729-47A4-A85E-E0EA38083E04}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>smarty_pants_bifocal_glasses</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Bifocal Eye Glasses</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The scientist, inventor and all-round intellectual Benjamin Franklin has unveiled his new &quot;double spectacles&quot;.\n\nThese eyeglasses, which might also be termed &quot;bifocals&quot;, are designed to aid those many persons unfortunate enough to have trouble distinguishing objects both close to them and far away. Consisting of a frame holding two half lenses over each eye, the lower lenses aid close vision whilst the upper assists with focus upon distant objects.\n\nWith this simple example of inventive insight, Benjamin Franklin has shared with us all a small part of his own admirably clear sight.</event_text>
<historical_date>1784</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEOAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{1996B87B-0CA3-4930-808C-9DB20E54A6FA}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>smarty_pants_cheats_electric_death</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Lightning is Electricity!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Due to the lengthy delay in constructing the Philadelphia church upon he wished to test his &quot;lightning rod&quot; - in order to channel lightning strikes to the ground without damage to people or buildings - American Philosophical Society founder Benjamin Franklin proposed an experiment in order to prove that lightning is indeed composed of electricity.\n\nThe theory states that electricity should be able to pass from the cloud to the ground via the wet string of a kite, with a key attached to attract the current. Following much speculation on the matter, Frenchman Thomas-Francois Dalibard has proved Franklin&apos;s theory by using a forty foot iron rod instead of a kite, observed electrical sparking from the cloud and survived.\n\nOther scientists have not been so lucky - Georg Wilhelm Richmann of St Petersburg was killed in the process due to insufficient insulation, leaving little behind but a smouldering pair of shoes. Upon completion of the church, Franklin fitted his sharpened lightning rod to its spire, stating &quot;The electrical fire would, I think, be drawn out of a cloud silently, before it could come near enough to strike&quot;.\n\nAlthough he has been proved correct, the Catholic Church in Europe have banned lightning rods as man-made objects designed to work against the will of God.</event_text>
<historical_date>1752</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvERAAAAkNOq8RAAAACQ06rxEgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEOAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{1F692D3E-BEA6-426C-8710-7E29E302D12F}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RIAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>society_of_jesus</key>
<picture_category>Religion_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Jesuits Expelled</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The Society of Jesus has been banned from Roman Catholic countries across Europe following political chicanery culminating in a Papal decree.\n\nAlthough rumours persist regarding a dispute between the Pope and the Crown Cardinals, it is widely believed that this move has little to do with matters of religion and a lot to do with the Jesuits’ control over trade revenues in those countries.\n\nAs such, the Society have been driven out of many regions by force, all their property and wealth confiscated by crown or government authorities.</event_text>
<historical_date>1773</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Religion_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{169C2F35-CEE6-4215-B23B-6D6B9DCE593E}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>south_sea_bubble</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The South Sea Bubble</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The South Sea Company was formed in order to refinance copious war debts at a bargain rate of six percent, with exclusive trading rights in the South Seas.\n\nEnamoured by the company’s lavish offices, and blinded by promises of a monopoly on trade with South America, investors bought as much stock as possible. Speculation began to spiral as ever greater numbers of shared were issued. Unfortunately, the company’s management were somewhat economical with the truth, lying to investors about the terms of trade, and encouraging all kinds of advantageous rumours to spread.\n\nWhen they finally got around to chartering a trading voyage – six years after the company was formed – the management realised that the profits available bore no relation to the perceived value of the stock, and began to secretly sell their own interests.\n\nNow word has spread that the management has sold out completely, panic selling has occurred  - in turn leading to an enormous stock market crash, the loss of many thousands of pounds, and the ruin of many individuals.\n\nThe government has stated its intention to stabilise matters, but the individuals responsible have fled to other countries to avoid prosecution.</event_text>
<historical_date>1720</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionTechExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;enlightenment_joint_stock_companies&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxBgAAAJDTqvEKAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEHAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{3D2861E0-C224-4AA0-AD53-D0D3B75A5E5D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QsAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>species_planetarum</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Species Plantarum</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The eminent Swedish naturalist Carl Linne - known as Linnaeus - has ensured a prominent place for himself as the &quot;father of modern taxonomy&quot; with the publication of his latest work &quot;Species Plantarum&quot;.\n\nThis mighty two-volume work lists every known plant, classifying them according to class, order, genera and species - using Linnaeus&apos; own unique system developed initially in his &quot;Systema Naturae&quot;. His simple system counts the pistils and stamens of every plant to group them into genera, enabling easy identification. Formal names are assigned to each plant, along with shorter epithets for ease of reference.\n\nRunning to over twelve hundred pages, Species Plantarum is already a monumental work, yet Linnaeus intends to continually update and expand it as new specimens arrive from his many correspondents around the world.\n\nMatters would appear to be (as the man himself has recently been heard to say): &quot;Deus creavit, Linnaeus disposuit&quot;, or &quot;God created, Linnaeus organised&quot;.</event_text>
<historical_date>1753</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAANAnHjg8AAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{0BDCDD07-B199-40C4-AA39-309EFFC50682}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjg8AAACQ06rxDgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>systema_naturae</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Systema Naturae</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Swedish doctor of medicine and botanist Carl Linne has published his &quot;Systema Naturae&quot;, a work that outlines a system of hierarchical classification of plants, animals and minerals.\n\nAlthough only a slim volume of some thirteen pages, Systema Naturae establishes Linne’s logical way of categorizing the natural world by class, order, genera and species. Though believing he is simply creating a catalogue of God&apos;s creations (and with many of the categorizations made for convenience sake rather than as an attempt to establish evolutionary relationships), the simple act of standardizing this process has brought a great degree of clarity to a complex subject.\n\nLinne is planning regular updates to his ongoing work, undoubtedly serving to aid the thoughts and insights of like-minded men in their efforts to understand the flora and fauna of the planet.</event_text>
<historical_date>1735</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{7C3BC81C-7D54-4037-94B0-0EA3EAE4342D}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>terribly_good_egg</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Bethesda Orphanage</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Twenty five year old evangelist preacher George Whitefield is setting a fine Christian example with the foundation of his Bethesda Orphanage, north of  Savannah, Georgia.\n\nBethesda, meaning &quot;House of Mercy&quot;, is intended to offer a safe home environment for poor orphans, also providing them with vocational training, discipline, and a strong Gospel atmosphere. The children will learn trades that should enable them to find gainful employment in adult life - including agriculture and weaving.\n\nMoney for the five hundred acre site has been provided by private donations and the money Whitefield himself collects at his ever popular religious meetings.\n\nHowever, Georgia is a difficult place for such a venture owing to its sparse population, yet Whitefield is a man of his word when it comes to spending the donations of others honourably, and is ploughing ahead with the project.</event_text>
<historical_date>1740</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QMAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{B0973334-56C4-451E-8806-381B8138D389}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>the_female_warrior</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Female Soldier!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Following the disappearance of her husband and the death of their daughter, Mrs Hannah Snell dressed in clothes borrowed from her brother-in-law and joined the Royal Marines at Portsmouth as a man in 1747.\n\nHaving sailed to the Indian Ocean, in 1748 she fought and was wounded eleven times in the legs and groin after being strafed by shot. Somehow she managed to avoid revealing her true gender to her colleagues until arriving back in London, where, with their encouragement, she sold her story to Robert Walker the publisher.\n\nAfter approaching the Duke of Cumberland in St James&apos;s Park, and regaling him with her adventures, Hannah secured her army pension from the Royal Chelsea Hospital.\n\nNow her story has been published as &quot;The Female Soldier&quot;, leading to further public attention and appearances on the stage in her marine uniform. Now she rightly intends to retire to run a tavern called &quot;The Female Warrior&quot; no less!</event_text>
<historical_date>1750</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QUAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{FF9393E9-9DB3-4F62-91ED-445C97916693}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>the_necklace_affair</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Necklace Affair</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Rumours are sweeping the French court in the wake of scandalous revelations! A priceless diamond necklace, intended as a gift for the old King&apos;s favourite courtesan prior to his death; has been stolen in an affair which casts all those involved in an unflattering light.\n\nIt would seem that a relatively minor noblewoman, the Comtesse de Lamotte, tricked Cardinal Rohan into parting with funds belonging to the Queen, and persuaded the jewellers Boehmer and Bassenge to part with the necklace in the belief that it was intended for the Queen, whose payment would follow.\n\nThe Comtesse subsequently fled with the necklace and is believed to have broken it up for sale before she was arrested along with Rohan and others, after the makers asked the Queen for payment. At their subsequent trial, all were acquitted, barring the Comtesse - who was sentenced to be whipped, branded and locked up in prostitute&apos;s gaol. In the end she was spared the physical punishments but was ruined in French society, eventually fleeing to England.\n\nHowever, questions continue to be asked about the Queen’s level of involvement in the case, as she was a known political enemy of Cardinal Rohan, and was visibly dismayed at his acquittal. Could it be that she played along with the fraud in order to ruin Rohan?\n\nRegardless of the truth, such an unsavoury case can only serve to underline the cavernous gulf between the lives of ordinary French people and those of their rulers.</event_text>
<historical_date>1785</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBQAAAJDTqvEIAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvEGAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{478DBDF0-4B2E-4630-BF15-3C27C5B59788}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QkAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>the_observer_published</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Observer</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Mr W S Bourne has published the first edition of his Sunday newspaper The Observer. The founder has states that it will &quot;share the spirit of enlightened Freedom, decent Toleration and universal Benevolence&quot; and be &quot;unbiased by Prejudice - uninfluenced by Party&quot;. Whether The Observer can remain a &quot;thorn in the side of the establishment&quot; is open to debate.</event_text>
<historical_date>1791</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>1</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBgAAAJDTqvEJAAAAkNOq8QUAAACQ06rxAQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEHAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{E94DD5AC-18CE-4B5C-B691-762B15353EA9}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QkAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>theatre_royal</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Theatre Royal</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The success of his &quot;The Beggar&apos;s Opera&quot; has provided actor-turned-manager John Rich with enough capital to commission the building of a &quot;Theatre Royal&quot; in Covent Garden (so named as it stands on the site of an old convent garden partially redeveloped by Inigo Jones in the 1630s into a piazza and church).\n\nAt the same time, a Royal Charter has been issued for a fruit and vegetable market adjoining the same piazza - presumably to keep the crowds supplied with ammunition if the production does not meet their standards!</event_text>
<historical_date>1732</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;grand_opera_house&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QYAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{FF977343-2E74-410D-A4D4-D8E6EAA64CB7}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>theatrical_censorship</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Theatrical Licensing Act</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Due to the current spate of &quot;satirical&quot; plays that seek to stir seditious anti-government thoughts in the minds of ordinary theatre-goers, a law has been passed giving the power of censorship to the Lord Chamberlain.\n\nAll new works must gain the approval of his office before they are staged. As a result of this draconian development, many authors are moving away from theatre and returning to novels, where their work will not be censored.</event_text>
<historical_date>1737</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;theatre&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QYAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{3FBD1E5F-16BC-4496-99AD-25822AAADDEA}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>titania_and_oberon</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Two New Moons</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Capitalising on his earlier discovery of a new planet, the astronomer William Herschel has discovered two moons in orbit around it. This latest discovery was made possible due to his continued advances in the construction of telescopes, of which he has made almost four hundred to date.</event_text>
<historical_date>1787</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEOAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{3FCECDD3-2FE5-4F85-BBC1-D53375714588}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>to_the_people_of_the_netherlands</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Aan het Volk van Nederland</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Dutch nobleman Joan van der Capellen tot den Poll has long been a champion of social reform in the Netherlands, campaigning tirelessly to overturn the last vestiges of feudalism in his country - to make all Dutchmen equal and no less.\n\nAs such, van der Capellen and his associates have become skillful in the ways of press manipulation and the use of satirical pamphlets to get their message across.\n\nNow that the sea-change of revolution has gripped the world, van der Capellen has taken the opportunity to stir change within his own country, publishing &quot;To the People of the Netherlands&quot; in secret - a pamphlet highlighting the benefits of a more republican political structure, with a popular constitutional monarch at its head.\n\nAlthough the pamphlet has been condemned by the Stadtholderate - of which high-born van der Capellen is technically still a member - it has proved most popular with the ordinary man, already reaching it’s third reprint! Meanwhile, the authorities have offered a substantial reward for information leading to the arrest of the author.</event_text>
<historical_date>1781</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvESAAAAkNOq8RQAAACQ06rxFQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEPAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6333436D-72A1-4313-AFD7-8AD7F6138C7B}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RUAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>top_hat_nuisance</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Top Hat!</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Haberdasher John Hetherington has caused a furore by further developing the current popular design of the beaver-skin riding hat into a fashion item, chiefly by drastically increasing the height, widening the brim and covering it with silk.\n\nUpon trying his &quot;top hat&quot; out on an experimental stroll through London in order to glean public reaction, imagine Hetherington’s surprise when dogs barked at him, women fainted and people ran away in fear. Before long there was a stampede and a number of injuries, eventually leading to his arrest and a court appearance where he was charged with wearing &quot;a tall structure having a shiny luster calculated to frighten timid people&quot; and fined fifty pounds.\n\nDespite getting an unprecedented amount of attention for a mere garment, and featuring in the daily newspapers, the top hat will clearly never catch on!</event_text>
<historical_date>1797</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxBgAAAJDTqvEJAAAAkNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvEHAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{7BA4372B-649B-4AC8-B20B-5699DF4205B8}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QoAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>transit_of_venus</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Transit of Venus</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Scientific expeditions have set out from many nations to observe the transit of Venus, a rare phenomenon in which the second planet passes in front of the Sun.\n\nSuch transits occur in pairs separated by eight years, and more than a century apart. They are an incredible opportunity to better inform ourselves about the motions of the celestial bodies, and, with such a scheme from the late Edmond Halley, scientists hope to pool their data to more exactly measure the distance of the Sun from the Earth.\n\nThough many of the expeditions are still returning from far-flung corners of the globe - their data unpublished - Mikhail Lomonosov has announced from his St Petersburg Observatory an exciting discovery of his own. Lomonosov observed a bright outline around Venus at the beginning and end of its transit, and has attributed it to the presence of an atmosphere around the planet which refracted the Sun’s rays to create the observed outline.\n\nFurther expeditions are planned for the 1769 transit, and this unprecedented collaborative effort by the scientific nations of Europe will surely lead to new and astounding revelations!</event_text>
<historical_date>1761</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8Q0AAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{39682F8D-1C0C-4F7A-9E86-4FA3B17132E3}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>trippy_dreams</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Dover&apos;s Powder</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Doctor Thomas &quot;Quicksilver&quot; Dover has had an interesting life. Beginning his career as a doctor in Bristol, he invested in shipping and privateering in the Caribbean, undertook a stint as ship’s surgeon, became captain of a slaver, fell foul of the East India Company’s thirst for revenue, and eventually became involved in the ill-fated South Sea Company at Buenos Aires - as one does.\n\nHaving found himself back in England and virtually bankrupt, Dover has since returned to the practice for which he was educated, at Cecil Street on The Strand, proving to be a fine doctor. Now at the age of seventy, Dr Dover has attracted a fine roster of patients by the publishing of his &quot;Ancient Physician’s Legacy&quot;, a guide to medical matters designed for reference in the home. Included in it is his recipe for what is now known as &quot;Dover’s Powder&quot; - a mix of Ipecac, Opium, Saltpeter, Tartare and Liquorice.\n\nThe powder works by inducing sweats to moderate temperature and regulate fever, as well as killing pain. As such, &quot;Dover’s Powder&quot; has found use in the Army and Navy, where it already benefits the sick and wounded.</event_text>
<historical_date>1732</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;naval_hospital&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QUAAABrj10cEQAAAJDTqvEGAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{37220EF2-7538-448A-9D4E-70457B707529}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>a49dHBEAAACQ06rxEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>vampire_attack_serbia</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Strange Case of Arnold Paole</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Following reports from across the empire regarding the spread of so-called vampirism, Regimental Field Surgeon to the Emperor, Johannes Fluckinger, has been assigned to investigate the situation.\n\nThirty days after he fell from a hay wagon and broke his neck, Arnold Paole was bothering the local populace in the village where he once resided. Paole sometimes told that he was haunted by a vampire and cured by smearing himself with the vampire’s blood and earth from its grave.\n\nAfter forty days in the grave, a further four deaths were attributed to his undead intervention, so Paole’s body was exhumed by order of the authorities and supervised by Fluckinger with the most illuminating of results! Of course Paole’s corpse was present, but it had not decomposed in any way, and the blood in his veins still flowed as if living. The nails on his hands and feet had also fallen off - to be replaced by freshly grown ones.\n\nConcluding that Paole must really be a vampire - and therefore responsible for the deaths in the village - a stake was driven through his heart causing him to bleed profusely and give an otherworldly moan! To be absolutely certain of his death Paole’s remains have been burned to ashes and tipped back into the grave. Of course proof of Paole’s vampirism is proof that he infected those he killed with his own malady, so each corpse has been afforded the same treatment.\n\nFluckinger is compiling his notes regarding this incident, along with other episodes of a similar nature, for his upcoming report to the Emperor &quot;Visum et Repertum&quot; - or &quot;Seen and Discovered&quot;.</event_text>
<historical_date>1725</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>FactionGovernmentType(&quot;gov_absolute_monarchy&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QQAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvERAAAAkNOq8RAAAACQ06rxEgAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QwAAACQ06rxEwAAAJDTqvEOAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{50DFEC23-7419-404A-AE8F-E840E11392B2}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>venus_mercury_occultation</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Occultation of Mercury</onscreen_name>
<event_text>On the evening of May 28th at the Royal Greenwich Observatory, the keen amateur astronomer John Bevis was lucky enough to witness the planet Venus passing in front of the planet Mercury.\n\nSince Venus is the larger of the two bodies (and thus obscured Mercury), the event is known as an occultation as opposed to a transit. For this event to occur it is necessary for an alignment of three planets: the two planets being viewed, and the planet from which the observation is made.\n\nThough such planetary alignments have occurred five times in the last four decades, ordinarily they are incredibly rare. Bevis is therefore the only man known to have directly witnessed the even rarer phenomenon of planetary occultation!</event_text>
<historical_date>1737</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions>FactionBuildingExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;royal_observatory&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QcAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{D6E94688-7FB2-4B3B-AA4F-839418C3932E}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>very_unpopular_book</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>De L&apos;esprit</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Chamberlain to the Queen Claude Adrien Helvetius, has caused a storm of argument by publishing a new philosophical work - &quot;De L’esprit&quot;.\n\nTaking an empirical viewpoint, he states that &quot;men are born ignorant, not stupid&quot; and argues that &quot;they are made stupid by education&quot; - that a new mind is a clean slate that learns from its senses and from the association of ideas. Therefore, good behaviour is entirely dependant on social environment and early association of pleasure and pain. Helvetius also argues that social welfare is best defined as the &quot;greatest happiness of the greatest number&quot;, and that having been trained to do good, the educated should be in a position to make life easier for those uneducated.\n\nFocusing on the implication that early association of pleasure and pain in itself involves an immoral act, both members of the church and many high-profile learned individuals have publicly attacked the book - leading even to a symbolic burning of the work by the hangman! Helvetius himself has already had to make three separate retractions of his ideas in order to calm the situation! Once again the readily available Encyclopédie, long known to be the source of all radical ideas, has been criticised also.\n\nIn private, empiricists wonder if the implication that the educated and wealthy have a social obligation to improve the lot of the poor, and that allowing the common man easy access to ideas (for example through a book such as the Encyclopédie) is the true source of the furore, as that would necessitate great upheaval in the current social system!</event_text>
<historical_date>1758</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEOAAAAkNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEMAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{DA013440-B214-4841-A6AD-323F823D399B}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q8AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>vivaldi_dies</key>
<picture_category>small funeral-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Vivaldi Dies</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The great Italian composer Antonio Vivaldi has died at the age of sixty three, following an attack of the &quot;internal fire&quot; from which he has suffered all his life.\n\nFollowing a recent downturn in the economic fortunes of his home city of Venice - where especially Baroque music has not oft been commissioned of late - Vivaldi decided to move to Vienna, as the Emperor was known to be an admirer of his work. Having sold most of his possessions and many of his original manuscripts, Vivaldi left Venice for Vienna, hopeful that he would obtain Imperial patronage to stage new operas. Unfortunately his untimely death has prevented this, the composer being buried at the Karlskirche in Vienna.\n\nDuring his lifetime Vivaldi composed around seven hundred pieces of music, his most famous being the landmark work &quot;Le Quattro Stagioni&quot; - &quot;The Four Seasons&quot;.</event_text>
<historical_date>1741</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>small funeral-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceODgAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAADQJx44OAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{BBF1DC59-088A-4D00-9A53-F97B46E579AC}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjg4AAACQ06rxDQAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>vivaldi_four_seasons</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Four Seasons</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The Baroque composer Antonio Vivaldi has produced four violin concertos of special interest amongst a wider piece of twelve he calls &quot;Il cimento dell’armonia e dell’inventione&quot; - &quot;The Contest of Harmony and Invention&quot;.\n\nThese first four pieces - each named after for a season of the year - have become known collectively as &quot;The Four Seasons&quot;, and have drawn far more attention than the remaining eight concertos within &quot;The Contest...&quot;. Each season has been subdivided into three movements - the middle movement being slower than the two that bookend it.\n\nThose lucky enough to have already heard The Four Seasons have noted Vivaldi’s has successful representation of the characteristics of each season within its musical textures.</event_text>
<historical_date>1725</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QkAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvELAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{91D48006-6CA3-4773-86F4-B5BF05F140C4}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>volta_electric_pistol</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Electric Pistol</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Italian professor Count Alessandro Volta has presented the latest in his series of electrical experiments to the leading scientific societies of Europe.\n\nOf particular note was his demonstration of the ignition of gases by an electrical spark, by which method his &quot;electric-phlogopneumatic pistol&quot; was seen to fire a cork for an appreciable distance, accompanied by an impressive &quot;pop!&quot; sound. This display is in keeping with current fashions of philosophical presentation, which often combine serious scientific reasoning with a pleasing element of showmanship.\n\nAs well as the more obvious martial implications of this new knowledge, Count Volta has suggested a long-distance communications device based upon it. Such a device would use iron rods to pass an electrical charge to a distant receiving station, there entering into a gas-filled vessel and resulting in an explosion indicating some predefined signal or message.</event_text>
<historical_date>1786</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QMAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{327F41D7-FF9A-426E-BD61-ED65FE1CA66C}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>voltaic_pile</key>
<picture_category>medicine_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Voltaic Pile</onscreen_name>
<event_text>In a letter to the Royal Society in London, the Italian scientist Count Alessandro Volta has unveiled the results of his experiments with electricity, including details of a curious device capable of storing and releasing a steady electrical charge.\n\nThe device, known as the ‘Voltaic Pile’, consists of alternating discs of copper and zinc separated by cardboard discs soaked in salt water. The metals, in combination with the conductive properties of the salt solution, produce an electrical charge. Volta hypothesises that this process is due to &quot;contact electrification&quot; - a form of static electricity.\n\nThough many questions remain unanswered, there can be no doubt that the Voltaic pile represents a vital step toward our understanding and mastering of that strange force electricity, and long may Count Volta’s work continue to this advantageous end!</event_text>
<historical_date>1800</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>medicine_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QMAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{7ECCAAED-F866-4FCB-8663-FA1CD6B0C0C2}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>voltaires_candide</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Candide</onscreen_name>
<event_text>&quot;Candide: ou l’Optimisme&quot; - &quot;Candide: or The Optimist&quot; is the writer Voltaire’s odyssey of an optimistic man who becomes transformed into a pessimist following a series of mishaps and incredible bad luck.\n\nThis latest opus has been lauded throughout the literary world due to both its wit and commentary on the human condition. Before preparing his manuscript Voltaire was struck by the misfortunes suffered by mankind due to a number of natural disasters, and attempted to reflect the powerlessness of man and how little control a man has over his life.\n\nThe publication of Candide has groundbreakingly been achieved simultaneously in five countries, and he is already working on revising and improving the text for further editions - surely thereby achieving substantially more than the author’s modest aim to &quot;bring amusement to a small number of men of wit&quot;.</event_text>
<historical_date>1759</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QcAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{B66C6BC3-8F64-43CC-A527-46F38A7AE5A4}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>wall_street_opens</key>
<picture_category>Politics_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The New York Stock Exchange</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The signing of an agreement by twenty four stock brokers under the spreading boughs of a buttonwood tree on Wall Street has heralded the founding of New York’s stock exchange.\n\nThe brokers are trading five securities, government bonds and bank stocks in exchange for commissions. The exchange is the latest milestone in the city’s ongoing economic expansion.\n\nFounded on the site of a very fine natural harbour, New York is integral to plans for the building of a canal linking the Great Lakes with the Atlantic Ocean - a scheme that would extensively open up trade on American soil and one which the city would no doubt profit greatly from.\n\nNo doubt the Wall Street brokers will shortly be lining up to invest in this most enterprising of schemes.</event_text>
<historical_date>1792</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Politics_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{B6F2222A-5F9A-4460-AB41-2E61D9C45DFC}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>waterford_crystal</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>1</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Waterford Crystal</onscreen_name>
<event_text>Brothers George and William Penrose have embarked upon a new enterprise in the city of Waterford, Ireland.\n\nTheir factory produces &quot;plain and cut flint glass, useful and ornamental&quot; and is swiftly establishing itself as the world’s foremost manufacturer of fine crystal.\n\nWith easy access to Waterford&apos;s busy port (and thereby the world&apos;s oceans), the business is ideally placed to serve a glowing global demand for its products - a demand fuelled by the growing prosperity which comes with the expansion of trade.</event_text>
<historical_date>1783</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions>FactionTechExists(&quot;britain&quot;, &quot;industry_textile_mass_production&quot;)</conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxBwAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QIAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvECAAAA
kNOq8QIAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEIAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6DF1BEC3-8016-4DDC-A644-3D501BF9C6C1}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>wesley_converted</key>
<picture_category>Religion_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Wesley Converts</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The activities of a non-conforming minister are attracting attention in British society.\n\nJohn Wesley is the son of a minister in the Church of England, and followed in his father’s footsteps by attending Christ Church College in Oxford. In the course of time he was ordained as a deacon and served in his father’s church before returning to Oxford to continue his studies. Wesley became a member of a religious group known as the &quot;Holy Club&quot;, whose members came to be known as Methodists, before travelling to America to minister to both colonists and natives.\n\nAlthough unhappy abroad, there was a positive aspect in that Wesley came into contact with the Moravian reformist sect - and he pursued this connection upon his return to England. Wesley’s own ideas about religious reform gradually took shape, and he has commented that whilst listening to Moravian sermons &quot;I felt my heart strangely warmed&quot;.\n\nWith his faith redoubled, Wesley has begun to preach sermons on salvation and grace, often outdoors to huge crowds as conforming churches closed their doors to him.</event_text>
<historical_date>1737</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Religion_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{FA5FF190-3444-4014-9760-5F3EB75203EA}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>wesley_methodism_chartered</key>
<picture_category>Religion_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Methodist Church</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The well-known non-conformist minister John Wesley has secretly ordained a number of ministers into his Methodist sect of the Anglican Church.\n\nWhilst Wesley has always maintained that he lives and dies as a member of the Anglican faith, this act is widely seen as officially dividing Anglicans and Methodists into two separate churches. Methodists base their faith around a belief in freewill and a determination to include worshippers from every section of society. Members are organised into local societies, and these are subdivided into classes for mutual instruction. Good works are seen as essential to the worship of God, as is missionary work.\n\nMany fear the passion of Methodist preaching, which at times strays perilously close to enthusiasm, and as such represents a threat to the established order.</event_text>
<historical_date>1784</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Religion_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QMAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEQAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxEQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDwAAAJDTqvEOAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{E97EBFCD-9A08-46BF-BF61-C7BD2994ED89}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8REAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>whitneys_cotton_gin</key>
<picture_category>Industry_european.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Cotton Gin</onscreen_name>
<event_text>American inventor Eli Whitney&apos;s new machine seems set to transform the cotton trade. As such he has acquired a patent for a cotton engine or &quot;gin&quot; - a device for automating the difficult process of separating cotton fibres from their sticky pods and seeds.\n\nA series of wire hooks mounted on a rotating drum draw the fibres through a screen, whilst wire brushes mounted on a second drum continuously remove the loose lint which would otherwise hinder the mechanism.\n\nIt is anticipated that this new invention will greatly aid the efficiency of the cotton production process and lower current manpower requirements. So useful in fact that Mr Whitney has already had to file a number of lawsuits for breach of patent by unscrupulous cotton producers attempting to use unlicensed versions of his machine.</event_text>
<historical_date>1793</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Industry_european.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvEMAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDQAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{7F66B053-77F1-4FE8-B98A-A4005280C1C0}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q0AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>wild_peter_hanover</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Wild Peter of Hannover</onscreen_name>
<event_text>A boy has been found living like a wild animal in the forest outside the city of Hanover.\n\nSince he is unable to speak - and may in fact be backwards in some way - nothing is known of the circumstances that led to his condition. It seems likely that he was abandoned when very small due to his handicap, and was not expected to survive exposed to the elements. Instead he has lived as a &quot;feral child&quot;, entirely outside of human society - walking on all fours and generally behaving in an animalistic fashion - and presumably learned to survive by purely by observing the animals of the forest.\n\nNamed Peter, the boy has been brought to England at the behest of the King, who has shown an interest in him. Following a great degree of curiosity from all quarters, &quot;Wild Peter&quot; - or more cruelly &quot;Idiot Peter&quot; - will continue to live there whilst attempts are made to stimulate his mind and eventually educate him, lest he remain a curiosity for the remainder of his natural life.</event_text>
<historical_date>1724</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCQAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QwAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCwAAAJDTqvEKAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{8BD8FB61-30C4-47E3-92DB-21850CB0839C}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8Q4AAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>witchcraft_austria</key>
<picture_category>agriculture_eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Austria Decriminalises Witchcraft</onscreen_name>
<event_text>In a reflection of the more enlightened and tolerant times in which we live, Austria has removed from the statute books laws allowing the torture and execution by burning of those suspected of witchcraft.\n\nIn the last century, accusations of witchcraft were commonplace and those who found themselves accused were invariably hanged, often on the flimsiest of evidence and at the behest of a baying mob with their own agenda. The social, political and religious upheavals which beset the previous two hundred years are undoubtedly to blame for this - with the feckless, the superstitious, the vindictive and the unscrupulous able to persecute vulnerable persons and unchallenged by any centralised authority.\n\nHowever, perhaps weary of turmoil, and under the steadying influence of reason, mankind finally appears to be coming to a realisation of the value of tolerance. Whilst the changes put in place in Austria do not condone those engaged in practices which might be construed as being witchcraft, they do go some way towards an acknowledgement that religious matters should not be so closely tied with those of state.</event_text>
<historical_date>1776</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>agriculture_eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAAA0CceODwAAAJDTqvENAAAAkNOq8QgAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAADQJx44PAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{DE05D1E0-4268-494C-8231-6413313428FD}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>NAnHjg8AAACQ06rxDgAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>witchcraft_britain</key>
<picture_category>Crime_European.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>Witchcraft Act Reformed</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The superstition, cruelty, and naked avarice associated with the persecution of so-called witches has been forever consigned to a bygone age, following the passing of a new British Witchcraft Act.\n\nPrevious acts removed the crime of witchcraft from the ecclesiastical courts, and saw it tried under common law instead. If the intention was to make the process fairer it was a total failure, as the property of those convicted of witchcraft went to the Crown, so local officials therefore had a stake in seeing a successful conviction. Due to this there was a significant rise in the number of hangings for witchcraft during the seventeenth century.\n\nThe new act views those who claim to have mystical powers merely as charlatans, punishing them with fines or imprisonment.</event_text>
<historical_date>1736</historical_date>
<season>season_winter</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>Crime_European.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEPAAAAkNOq8QsAAACQ06rxEAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QoAAACQ06rxDgAAAJDTqvENAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{2775C8B6-324F-4364-99D3-77E966B7D25F}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8RAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
<events>
<key>yale_founded</key>
<picture_category>culture-eu.tga</picture_category>
<dynamic>0</dynamic>
<onscreen_name>The Collegiate School of Connecticut</onscreen_name>
<event_text>The Collegiate School of Connecticut has opened its doors to students for the first time, becoming the third higher education establishment in the colonies.\n\nFormer Harvard alumni have contributed books from their personal libraries to create the library for this new school of divinity.\n\nThe Collegiate School was intended to remain a beacon of puritan thought in an increasingly unorthodox world, and in 1718 the governors contacted a man named Elihu Yale for further funding. The devout Yale, a Welsh businessman and philanthropist, had £560 to contribute from his trading successes with the East India Company, over four hundred books of his own and a portrait of the King - all which he gave gladly.\n\nThe school’s name-change was mooted as an encouragement for further investment, but sadly when news of the change reached Yale’s family in Wales he had already died - whilst on a further business trip to India.</event_text>
<historical_date>1701</historical_date>
<season>season_summer</season>
<conditions></conditions>
<picture>culture-eu.tga</picture>
<Gen_conditions>0</Gen_conditions>
<Gen_event_text>0</Gen_event_text>
<s_ColLineage>kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCAAAAJDTqvELAAAAkNOq8QcAAACQ06rxDAAAAJDTqvEBAAAA
kNOq8QEAAACQ06rxCgAAAJDTqvEJAAAA
</s_ColLineage>
<s_Generation>0</s_Generation>
<s_GUID>{6C4B5D5F-3114-470E-A769-C05AFAA1815E}</s_GUID>
<s_Lineage>kNOq8QwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==
</s_Lineage>
</events>
</dataroot>
